<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-basketball/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1893-04-01/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Basket+Ball+Game+Indoor+Sport</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NOW FOR A NEW GAME
Baticing Baae Ball inCaml In
stitute Gyuasuiuu.
A GAME ALL CAN PLAY.
>a"er nianean r @Medsee-A Osmbinmttm
et haswases and feet natI-36e Ned eor
Deun-e.ss-A pset Reeuiring indsabnm
Tse laus ethe Game.
N INDOOR BPORT
which is new to this
city has bees iatre
duced by Mr. MauaI
A. Joyce, the athletic
instructor at the Car
roll Istitute. The
game has met with
great popularity is
other places where it
has been played, and
from the interest which
it hnt excited among
the members of the
Carroll Institute is bids fair to asset with the
Succes here that it bas in other cities. Almost
owery might basket bell is played in the gym
anshetts the institute, and the sport is not only
Smithy and invigerating, but exciting and full
ot interest.
Bushet ball wva Arst started about a year ago
ad ree that time it hes spread throughout
Se esuntry esecially in the gymnasiums of
he yong Men a Christian asociatioss. It is
paticularly adaptable to business men. as little
narmarx A. Joyce.
se metpractice is required to learn it and there
6, no incident roughness if the rules are
stictly adhered to. It is the intention of Mr.
deyce is try to have other teams formed in the
symmasisme in the city and to have regular
entestn between them. It eomameade itself in
s it can be played in almost any sized room
den any had of lot. whether it be large or
mail, and that the number of player. need
only be limt. I b the size of the ground. It
bkings into play all maseles of the body. thus
being a healthy exercise, and at the same time
te a ws incidens to moet sports are want
1. The only apparatus neessary for the
oe to be played is a regular Rugby foot ball
mnd re half-bushel baskets.
movwr rT PL 6TD.
Theegh she courtesy of Mr. Joyce a Stan
aoprter witnessed a game of basket ball played
M the Carrer Institute on one of the evenings
of this week. The two baskets are attached to
th =anig strack at the opposite ends of the
gymmsam and U.s object of the game is to
Shen e heU in the opponent'e basket. The
uame consist of mine men each. made up of a
gaiheeper. two backs to assist him. a center, a
eight and left henter, two forward and a home
ma. They are arranged in this order from
Oe gnal whica they are defending. It is not
asessmry that the players thou!d remain in
teir glaces. but they should move in such a
way as to gie the forward player an oppo:
baesy Is gee a good tos at the goal or the
baecks to keep theer opponents from obtaining
so mmm by taking it from thea when they are
ghbntsto throw. It is the luty of the goal
ba~to beep the ball away fromi the vicinity.
etgoal. end it is more often neessary for
hi to bat the bail with his had tha for
e~er meambers of the seama to do so.
L. Serim. 3. leeward
4.ame.. eae...
4. Sm. .a.5
en.. ...s-....e.
The game is started by the teems lining up
ba their respseutve positions and then the
safeae tomes the ballian the air, It must not be
te.-d antal it strikes the ground. Thea the
players ean catch it. and the object of the one
who obtains it isto pass istso one of the players
ahis own sidec.who either passes itto inotherwho
msay be in a favorable position to tom f~ar goal
or else attempts to auake a goal himself. To
bee a foot bal into a basket euasiended ten feet
a cen SsA.av
beG airani eiasest lags en~t. held it.ie
net en eas messean means, end thee.
thanmy ethe at guat are madebut
as t ase -s eemtl, and e sensty
ohB~in meds. esnammty, an the
qshad esty. The haDeam be aoma
an ists with -n or beth --a-~
In bM the sesm s e 40 -a -e
e be h ss:
asmmmS he es h the det er hased
A e esms e with te hasb mUs
am thmm... ..a. a. he
Gotas o ben shile rmaI and Mas to stop
The har maw be held in ds baud The arms
Iee or bod soat not be used for blding it.
If h lb is beld for any length of time th
referee tess it into the air. as in the baegtnmg
of theam
o the5 ein, holding, J~n .trp, n
or striking b allowed. The t iafringem m
'f this rule eosnts a foal and a second dis
q"mli= a player, but, as in foot ball, a substi
tats may take his place.
IN TaN BAsKET. C
When a ball goes out of bounds it is put in
play in the same way as in a foot ball game.
The game consists of two halft of twenty
minutes each or such time as the captains may
decide on. and time is taken out for delays.
A goal counts three points and a foul one
point for the opponent. and a majority of the
points decides the game.
There are a referee and umpire, whose duties
are the same respectively as the same officials
in a foot ball game.
Any player has a right to get the ball at any
time while it is in the field of play. provided
that he handles only the ball and not the op
ponent.
ADVANTAGEs OF THE GAME.
To an observer the game seemed to be one
that will solve the problem, which has been a
knotty one for some time, of introdncing a
game which will meet the excitement incident
to most outdoor sports and at the same time
be suitable for indoor play. At present when
the outdoor season closes most of the athletes
drop tbe sports in which they have been in
terested and the benefits thev derived from
them are lost. This game is one that requires
skill and agility. but strength is not one of the
necessary factors. and, consequently. men of
all physical conditions can take part in it. It
has also been found to have been a useful
sport for girls and women, as it is especially
APTEn THE FALL.
adapted to securing good health without having
the nervous strain caused by some of the
sports now indulged in.
In its principli. it is a combination of foot
ball and lacrosse. It resembles foot ball in
most of the rulings, but in the method to be
pursued to obtain a goal the game more closely
resembles lacrosse. Although at first glance it
would hardly seem possible to have any amount
of team play in the game, still it is only by the
concerted action that a team can play to the
beet advantage. A novice in the game inva
riably feels disposed when he obtains the ball
to make a shot for the goal, which could not be
made from any distance one time in a hundred,
as in order that the ball should remain in the
basket it has to be skillfully and easily tossed,
not thrown. A good player will. when he has
the ball, quickly look for one of his own team
who is in an uncovered position to whom he
can tos it. In this way a well-drilled team
could almost entirely keep the ball from the
hands of a team made up of new men. Quick
ness of eye, hand and foot is one of the first
requisites for a good player, and he also must
keep his head about him. A moment's hesita
tion or a wrong pass may give considerable
advantage to the other side.
If an umpire is chosen who strictly follows
the rules of the game there is little chance for
any roughness, as running with the ball is
prohibited, and thus the injuries coming from
sharp tackling in foot bal are done away with.
The attention of the player is fastened on the
ball and personal feeling in the matter is lost
sight of. The object of each player when one
of his side obtains the ball is to place himself
in an uncovered position so that one of his own
team can pays it to him, while the opponents
should in this eae stick closely to the men
with whom they are paired so that a pass to
them would gave an equal opportunity for each
to catch the ball. It is in this respect that
cool-beadedt.euand quickness count. Idi
vidlual play on the part of one man will destroy
all the good work that the rest of the team may
do. If the game in played indoors in a gym
naisium the passee should be more of a toes
rather than hard straight throw.
As the game has apparently obtained a good
foothold in this city and as it is a healthful and
at the same times exciting sport it is to be
hoped that the efforts of Mr. Joyce to make the
game a popular one in this city will meet with
success, Some of the men under him are bo
conming quite proficient and before long he will
have a iirst-class team,</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014635/1893-04-21/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Game+Sport&st=text&r=-0.268,-0.077,1.536,1.536,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Basket Ball as Playod in Y. M. O.
A. Gymnasiums.
Mj
ClifcliertcyE"i,j-,h EVrsetraM ?m&
JK. MIS
sure, 2l-v' litl. Unl5t, n-I M
k -UfisS&iJsiv ""Pl?
ft
t&Wj
7"s "TwVi
A f
ftUVJtoir tfifiT-I b tuu t.l3 j Tnl?) VSy
ChnA!lpr. Jff a 6ienntt ft iir- v
!(jaudnlr..J fit AtD'ss'ti ..t.ri'S-.
"ltr-Ucr for I cUf" Sr vi fr -ctrir
Vnll. 1U.1MK. r-ia Hmtr 1 f
mw,t iipi-'in".' tt BcsraKi
THOMAS F. BAYARD.
STb Xtoiiorab'-a Career' at Onr 2Vew Am
lMador to J Cngantf.
Thomas Francis J 'ayard, the new
Bmbassaaicrto the con rt of. St. Jamets
-cvas borchi Wibninglton, Del., in 1S2S.
Ecrras fitttidfor a m:rca;atiIo life-ami
f-
IF
II OX. TnOMAS T. BATAHD.
placed in a businessliause in Xew York
.Hty. He returned to "Wilmington in
1S48, studied In vr, and -was admitted to
tho bar in 18rl. He was appointed
United -States -district attorney for Del
aware, but resigned tin- following yer.
"n 18'r he reciox d to Philadelphia,
-ivheiehe becamo the partner of Vil
liam bliippeu. He returned tolVilraing--son
and succeeded Ins father to the
.United State.- senate in 1S08. ITe was
reelected in lc7o and again jn ISl. ?k.
Cleveland appointed him scrctarj' of
Atate iu 1SS5. On tho day -on which he
was olecU-d to the serrate for a full
term his father was also reelected a
A Knme for lloth Sexe It Is Something
Like 1'i.otball, I'.ut Has No Hough
features and J 5 Full
or Fun.
For a long1 time gymnasium instruc
tors were confronted by the necessity
for a game which could be played in
doors by old and young, male and fe
male. They wanted a game devoid of
lough features, yet one which should
be thoroughly scientific, and which
should atford plenty of opportunity for
good healthy exercise for the scholar
or business man, and training for the
athlete, feuch possibilities, says the
New York Sun. have been discovered in
the game of basket ball, which has be
come so popular in Fchool and club
fjjnnnasiums throughout thp country.
The (fame was first introduced by the
directors and pupils of the Y. M. C. A.
fill
tSOAI.3.
training school at Springfield, Macs.
Its advantages were t,oon perceived,
and the sport, spread to the gymnasiums
controlled by the Young Men's Chris
tian association, and was further in
troduced in scholastic institutions and
club gymnasiums. At the training school
Ihc g.iuic was developed, and a strong
team was drilled in the simple work
ings of it by James Naismlth, one o the
Springfield instructors, and an earnest
worker in i be Held of all-around sport
and recreation. In New York and
senator lVoui Delii ware to-servo for tha IJrooklyn.are sereral good teams, and
unexpired fl of his original term. H1 P'V "lt; a ir"IU w' l-l"ie-
This is the only case cf a father and The game can readily be played in al-
-sonLeing voted for by tho same icgis- ost the smallest gymnasium. As the
lature to fill the senatorial office. In sizeb of tht! exercising rooms vary, the
vpnate he served on tho committees sjauie purycu uy cuii iwiu ia suKuiy
on finance, judiciary, prh'atc land
rlaims, libiary and revision ofDaws. In
1SS1 ho was elecrcd president pro tem
nore of the senate. He was a.candi-
different. All th match games axe
played under regular rules, however,
-andth" peculiar disad vantage which a
"gym" may have for the visiting team, is
idate for president in ISSO and 1S54. In- remecieil so Xar as possible. Hie game
Wudinghigrest-rraiidfather, Gov. Has-, can be played out of doors on a large
Ptt. h i the fifth member of his fam- umuiibwcu an i .11 Syw
r 1 i. iin?iim. rrin r
piy wni) nave oecnpicu seats 111 11191
jUnitfldita,tes senate,
WHEELMEN'S PRIZE CUP.
r9 Be Competed Vov at tho Gr(At Kce
j The League of Ameiiean TVlieclmen
iJUavo been presented with a very hand
jsomo -trophy to baxrapcted for in their
;Sntcrna,tannal jaco meet, to bo held at
idiica'o next? Augnst, Il&nry Ij. Sal- j
fojistall, a. memUT of the Elizabeth A.
jfff Wheelmen, is the donor of the prize.
jit is a sterling bilvcr cup, gold lined,
itod stands twenty-eigBt inches high ou Jl". "v
The goals pictured in this col
umn arc iised, the upright one for the
field, on wliich it can be placed at any
point, and the other for Indoor play.
The latter is attached to the gallery or
the wall of the room. The string is
used to turn the goal so that tho ball
may readily be regained. These goals
are the improved article The first
goals, from which the game got its
name, were only peach baskets nailed
to tho wall or running tiack.
The game can be played by a number
of men at once. In a small jrvmnasium.
howover, flvo aside is the most con-!
In larger rooms nine
men can piay on a biae. Lnis is con
sidered the regular, number, and they
are placed a -hown in the accompany
ing illustration. Tho game itself is
strictly one of passing the ball fiom
man to man. It can neither be kicked
nor batted with the fist. The object is
to get the ball into the basket or goal.
A large person is useful, but one of the
best players it tho Twenty-third
htreet Y. Jf. C. A. gymnasium is
a little hap not much oTer
GOAL,
KOMT
iTjsagvtfROi.
imitTPimimmmm,
XV
aT&slr araxzE xt the iszesjtjltioxai.
-iix-inch ebony base. The figure of
jFamtttnding upon a globe surmounts
phe lid. 'The jieadsof Bacchus and Icr
WuTy ndorn the arms of the urn, under
(wliich ro American eagles. Tho Tj. A.
pVV. emblem is engraved upon ihc back.
The cup-will be a perpetual challenge
trophy, and the -conditions under winch
It wiil -bo .competed for will be deter
ruined rupon by thcxacing "board of the
league Jt is tho most valuable prize
ver -donated .to the L. A. W. by any in
diridiiol onem.bttr of the organization.
It WiIi"boxacedJorannuallv.
1.
"Upcf, Lfuicmt uuil Clieen." j
1 An American naval officer says that i
once4 -wheal -a great function took place
5n the harbor of Cherbourg, several
.vessels of our American squadron vcre
present ,asd wcie drawn up in line to
baluto the rmpress' yacht as it passed,
Kiyss an article on the navy. TheTTrcnch
ffailors-manned the yards of their -ship s
xuid Blio-uted: Yire l'lmpci-strice!"'
Ivnow ing tliat he could not school his
men to repeat those woids in the brief
Sirao left to him, the American admiral
Wrderefi his crerr to cry: "leef. lemons
Jiud cheese. Tlie imperial yacht came
sweeping on, and as it reached the licet
amlghtj' roar went up of "Beef, lemons
jicd cheese" that entirely drowned the
toIcos of the Frenchmen. And the em
yreR 6aid she had never been so compli
tnented. T'acla Abut Ire-l.iad. t
The population of Ireland in 1S91, ac
fcording to the revised return- just is
uad, was 4,0sl.2-,S. The natural in
crease of population, or eeex of births
Uver death, for the year was '22.117, and
S ho loss by emigration wns 59.023; 21.
75 marriages were registered within
"the year, and it significant of the re
ligious feeling which exists in all parts
ol Ireland that only 399 were by civil
oontracts in the registrars' ofticesT
wftHnjKiin
?'G0AL
POSEMOXS OF TITE FLAYTJIS.
four feet tail. To get an un
covered position is of the utmost im
portance, as the player can thus easily
get the ball and as easily pass it to one
of his side near the goal. It requires a
great deal of practice to put the ball in
the goal, wliich is placed at some dis
tance above the players' heads. 2Cbt
alone must a pla-or be bkillful, he
must also be very lively. A player
must thiow the ball from the spot
w here ho catches it, but ho can turn
around to throw it. 2vo interference is
allowed, and tackling and pushing are
strictly prohibited. A player may only
obstruct the passage of the bail after it
is thrown.
When the game is played 011 a field
the player may run with the ball if he
continually throws it above his head
and cr.tcho it again. The ball may
also be diibbled along the ground with
the hand.
Tt-.di play counts for everything in
basket play. Tlie t.wo forwards and
the home man should always work to
gether to get the ball into the goal.
The backs guard the goal, and the cen
ter men are supposed to get the ball
and pass it forward toward the home
man.
The game is usually played in two
halves of fifteon minutes each, with a
slight intermission. When a goal is
made the same goes right on. It is
perhaps the fastes' game played to
day, and is played with a snap "which
football player in lining up may well
.RUSSIA</text>
      </result>
    </results>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86088296/1893-06-01/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Game+Sport+Indoor&st=text&r=-0.322,-0.082,1.643,1.643,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE GAME OF BASKET BALL.
Interesting and Exciting Sport For Thos
Not Able to Exercise Kegularly.
The unnounceinent that at a woman's
educational institution not far from this
city tho students played a close and ex
citing game of "basket ball" wasperhaia
the first item which attracted public at
tention to a sport that is rapidly becom
ing very popular in this country among
those who have neither the physique nor
the taste for baseball or football. The
rules of the new sport are comparatively
simple, and the ease with which the
fundamental laws of the game can be
acquired in a few minutes' practice have
served to make it popular wherever it
has been introduced, while its freedom
from much of the roughness and intri
cacy of football has also tended to make
the devotees of basket ball enthusiastic
in their praise of its merits.
The name "basket ball" is derived from
the fact that scores are made not by car
rying the ball across the goal lines or
kicking it over the goal bar as in foot
ball, but by throwing the spheroid into I
a moderately small basket, which is hung
about 10 feet above the ground or floor.
To accomplish Buch a feat usually re
quires much practice, and as a rule tho
try at goals are far more numerous than
tho scores. Either hand or both hands
can be used in holding the ball, and it
must either he thrown or be batted with
tho open hand a punch with the fist or
arm, or a kick, constituting a foul.
The game differs from football also in
tho fact that no player is allowed to run
with the ball, but must stand where it is
caught, and a fair catch can be made
only with the hands. If the ball is held
for an unnecessarily long time, the um
pire takes possession of it and puts it
"ia play" by throwing it in the air, no
player being allowed to touch it in such
an event until it has struck the ground.
If a ball goes out of bounds, it is put in
play as in football, and no player is "off
sido," but every player has the right to
touch the ball anywhere or everywhere
in the game, provided the ball is in play.
No pushing, tripping, 6hoving or tac
kling is allowed, and every such offense
constitutes a foul, which gives one point
to the opposing nine. As a goal counts
but threo points and a foul one. there is
every incentive to avoid rough play. The
players advance the ball by tossing it to
some member of their own nine, and
there is the best opportunity for success
in personal skill combined with good
team play. The "forwards" and "cen
ters" usually toss the ball forward, but
when it gets dangerously near his own
goal, the goalkeeper often bats it with
tho open palm.
Ono advantago which basket ball has
over many other forms of popular sport
lies in tho fact that, while it allows 18
players to participate, it can be pursued
tho year round in tho open air during
tho warmer months and in the gymna
sium whilo cold weather prevails. Again,
basket ball can be played by persons
whose physique is not of tho most robust
type, although many athletes also have
found, in it a healthful form of exercise.
It has pypved of great value In furnish
ing exercise for business men, women
and children, as wpll as brawny students,
and from the general success it has al
ready attained wherever it has been in
troduced there is every probability that
basket ball will soon become a very popu
lar and widespread form of outdoor and
indoor sport. Boston Advertiser.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058130/1894-11-25/ed-1/?sp=13&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Sport+Game+Indoor+Outdoor</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BASKET BALL
JTHAMChGIVIXO GAlE 31ETWEEX
oPlioUORES AXD IRESllJIE
3 Iopular and Graceful Game bat
Has Foiinil Great Favor AnioiiK
Girls Some of the Rules nUll HeK
iilations Observed in PlajinK1 It
Basket ball is to tie womens col
lege what football is to the mens
The Bryn Mawr girls are particu
larly enthusiastic over this sport and
the Smith college students are in train
ing for a match game some day
Thanksgiving week
A picked nine from the sophomore
class will be pitted against a picked
nine from the freshmen class The
Smith college girl is immensely inter I
ested in basket ball which she also
calls cradle ball
1
I j
I
r
r
j
1DiUikct For IIKIOOM
Daslcct Vac Outdoor
L At Bryn Mar the students are
equally as devoted to this game in
deed their interebt in it is tremendous
and vies with 5 oclock teas and the
atricals in mitigating the ennui l of var
sity life The freshman and sopho
more classes are particularly alive to
this sport Miss Elsa Bowman is the
captain or the sophomores nine while
Miss Corlnne Putnam is the leader of
the freshman
WHY THE GAME IS POPULAR
The beauty of tne gameor one of I
I its beauties for it has manyis that II
it can be played by any number and
the more he merrier it is usually i
J
J voted The ideal number however is
nine on each side There is a goal I
keeper two backs to assist a center
a right and left center two forwards I
and a home man I e a woman in this
c1 TJ y
Tire accompanying diagram shows
the positions of the players
The end and aim of the game is to
toss a ball which is the size of a small
football into one of the two large bas
kets suspended at each end of the field
The winning side is the one that lands
the ball in the opponents basket The
basket is placed about ten feet high
When the game is played in the
gymnasium the basket Is bracketed to
tb side of the wall For outdoor use
it is supported at the same height by
au upright post The price of the bas
Jets or goals is 15 per pair for in 1
door use when supplied with a pipe
or post for outdoors the cost is some
what more The balls which are cov
ered with Jeather and about twenty
A four inches in circumference cost
about 3 each a rubbercoated ball
J can be purchased for 115 1
Basket ball can be played in a gym I
nasium in a large room or a small
b 1 HeW 01 a large field if in the latter I I
as many as thirty or fifty players may I
take part I
APPROPRIATED BY WOMEN I
The man who originated the game j
01 invented it or whatever the proper
word may be did not intend it merely
for amusement his idea was to pro i
vide a good allaround physical exer
cise and as such it cannot be im
P oyed upon combining as it does run
ning jumping bending pnd twisting
nearly every muscle and joint in the
body is brought into exercise
Mr James Naismith of Springfield i
Mass originated basket ball about
I
three years ago As soon as it became
known among the gymnasiums it
spread like an fclHdenfie Primarily
intended for young men for whom
most of the good things of life are in
tended it was soon taken up by young
women who declared that If there
was anything good in the game they
would like io become acquainted with
itThe
The girl forthwith bought a book of
rules which they masteredin very
brief order donned their gymnasium
ostumes and began playing at once
The fine points of the game however
Were only acquired by practice
I RULES OBSERVED
j The three players ivho are designat
ilL ed as forwards occupy the third of
the ground nearest the opponents
pwal the centers occupy the middle
third and the backs the defensive
third of the ground The forwards
of one team stand near the backs of
the other
Out of doors with plenty of room
the field may be 150 feet long the goal
lines running through the baskets per
pendicular to the length of the field i
the side boundaries 100 feet apart
The ball is put in play IJ by the icferee 1
throwing it up in the middle of the
field this is done at the commence
ment of the game at the beginning of
the second half after each goal and J
when a foul has been made The time
of play is two halves of twenty min I
utes each I
A goal is made when the ball is I
Yf thrown or batted from the ground into
the basket provided it stays in It is
a foul if the ball Is struck with the
I fijts or kicked
The ball must be held by the hands
fl
0
i
the arms or body may not be used for
I holding it
No pushing tripping shouldering or
striking is allowed infringements of
this rule count as a foul
The score is counted by points A
goal counts three points a foul one
point for the opponents A majority of
points decides the game</text>
      </result>
    </results>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84023253/1895-01-25/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Basketball+Basket+Ball+Game+Games+Sport+Baskets</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BASKET BALL.
Those who were interested in the
basket ball games played last winter
will be pleased to learn that the town
and school boys are tohaveonemore
battle for the supremacy. A word
about the game which has become so
popular in the past few years will
be interesting to those who enjoy
good honest sport.
Basket ball was invented in 1889 by
ames Nuismith, teacher in the interna
tional training school, Springfield. Dur
ing its first season it wasnot particularly
popular hut has gained in favor and may
now be called quite as important sport in
the Y. M. C. A. world as football and
baseball, but it is essentially an indoor
game and the interest that is excited in
an exercise confined to the gymnasium
can perhaps never equal the zest which is
thrown into a game like football, played
under the blue of heaven, in the fresh out
door atmosphere and sun's rays that seem
to penetrate the muscles ot the athlete
and impart added vivacity. However,
at the season when football bruises have
long ago healed and conquests on the
gridiron are matters for rumination, he
who sighs for the pigskin can find much
satisfaction in basket ball, it possessing
all the elements of football but, if rules
are enforced, lacking the excessive rough
ness. The ball used is perlcctly round,
made of a rubber bladder, covered with
leather and is about a foot in diameter.
Briefly outlined the game according to
official rules for 1805, is played as follows:
baskets especially constructed tor the
purpose, are placed in a vertical position
with the mouth ten feetlrom the ground,
one at each end of the field (gymnasium),
occupying much the same position in re
lation to the players as do football goals.
i ne competitive teams tane positions on
the field as in football, save that there is
no line-up, The teams are composed of
five men when the playing space is less
than 1800 square feet, seven when it is
more than 1800 and less than 3600 and
nine men when over 3600. The referee,
with a player from each side, takes posi
tion in the center. He puts the ball in
play by throwing it up. Which side has
first ball depends on which center man
secures it. The ball is not kicked or
struck with the fists but thrown or batted
with the flat of the hand and the object
is, to get it into the basket, doing which
scores a goal. On the number of goals
secured depends the victory. The net
work of rules which govern the action of
the game is quite as elaborate as football
and will not be given here. Suffice it to
say that spectators easily comprehend
its action. The putting of a ball into the
basket may seem a veryeasv thing to do
but as a matter of fact it is very difficult
to acomplish with the floor empty and,
of course, much more so when two teams
are at strife. One of the rules says that
the ball shall always be kept in motion.
Two twenty-minute halves are played
with a rest of ten minutes between "the
halves. This is the time of actual play.
Each side has itscaptain while position
is the same as in baseball. The referee is
judge of the ball. He is the superior offi
cer ot the game and decides all questions
uul ucuimciy lulling on me umpire, i lie
umpire is judge of the men, calls all fouls,
notifies the offenders and has power to
disqualify men.
The game which was to be played
on Thursdayevening of this week has
been postponed until Saturday even
ing. The two teams have been prac
tising faithfully and will be able to
play a very interesting game. It is
hoped that the public will turn out
and encourage the gymnasts, as all
the proceeds over and above the ex
penses are to go towards much need
ed new apparatus for thegymnasium.
AMONG THE FRATERNITIES.
Moose River encampment, I. O.O.
F., has accepted an invitation from
the encampment at Littleton, and
will work a degree on candidates be
fore the encampment at that place
this evening.
The convocation of the fourth
Masonic district will be held here next
Thursday commencing at 3 o'clock
in the afternoon. Harley P. Sea ver of
Barton, D. D., G. H. P., will have
have charge of the meeting and the
work of the several Capitular degrees
will be exemplified. A banquet will
be served a 6 o'clock.
The entertaiument given by Cham
berlin Relief Corps last week Thurs
day evening for the benefit of the
Lyndonville Relief Corps was quite
well attended and a nice literary and
musical programme was carried out.
Thomas Shufelt and W. B. Atwood
sang solos, George Felch gave a pic
colo solo and readings were given by
Miss Blanchard and Miss Balch.
Miss Gorham presided at the piano
and a promenade closed thetvening's
entertainment.
MASQUERADE.
About 150 people attended the
masquerade at Pythian Hall last
Friday evening. The costumes were
appropriate to the occasion some
being very good.
Good music was furnished by the
St. Johnsbury orchestra. Coffee and
cake were served and a good time
was enjoyed by all. The entertain
ment was given by the Mite society
of the Church of the Messiah, anil
was a success socially and financially,
as about thirty dollars was taken at
the door.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1895-11-26/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Play+Games+Game+Foot+Sport&st=text&r=-0.249,-0.075,1.499,1.499,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TO PLAY TWO GAMES
Interest in Foot Ball to Be Divided
Thursday.
INTERESTING BASKET BALL CONTEST
Party of Cyclists Wheel to Annap
olis.
GENERAL SPORTING NEWS
The devotees of foot ball ln this city will
have plenty of chance to gratify their de
sires Thanksgiving day with a game at
Capitol Park between the Columbian Uni
versity and the Columbia Athletic Club,
and one at National Park between the
Orient and Potomac athletic club?. The
first game will probably have the largoat at
tendance, but the latter will have all the
advantages that a good fieli and two even
ly maUhctl teams can give.
The selections for the university team
have narrowed down until there are not
more than a couple of contestants for each
position, while some of the places have
been filled permanently. Taylor will play
left guard, Cockrell rlglit half, Beard left
half and Weaver full back. Center lies be
tween Johnson and Harlan, right guarii be
tween Hicks and Clapp; right tackli, Shus
ter or Gambilll; left tackle, D. Fugitt or
Doolittle; right end, Hra-.vuer or Wagner,
quarter back, Mills or McDowell, and left
end, Harris or Baker. With the candl
?lntes on hand that are now on paper, an
exceptionally strong team should be made
up that would give the C. C. a hard tus
sle.
The game at National Park will also be a
most Interesting one. The Potomacs and
Orients are both string teams, and as some
people think, should have played the C.
A. C. it-stead of the Columbian University.
The two teams played not long ago, and
neither side was able to score a point, so
that the cornine cont?st bids fair to be ex
ceptionally hnlliant in the matter of plays.
The recent game between these two teams
also deserves a word for Its clean playing,
which was entirely free from unnecessary
roughness and ung?.itlemanly conduct.
The Potomacs were defeated by the Gal
laudets by a small score, wnile the Orients
played the same team to a standstill. The
only defeat of the Oliente was administered
by tho Baltimore aggregation Saturday.
The game will be called promptly at roon.
maw (?oui) PLATS (in:i:iti:i).
An InlercNtliiir ??'ime of Bitaki-t
Hull.
The game of basket ball played last
evening ln the rifle gallery of the National
Guard between the teams of the Y. M. C.
A. and the Cycle Corps was one of the
cleanest, hardest-fought games that has
been played in the series. Although the
Cycle Corps came out victorious by a score
of to 1, they had to work with all their
energies to attain that end, and several
times It looked squally for them.
It has been claimed by several persons
Interested In the game of basket ball that
the contests were degenerating Into wres
tling matches and slugging bouts, with a
little foot ball thrown in, but last evening's
game demonstrated that basket ball can be
played as lt should be. if the players will
only conform to the rules. A number of
persons were present to witness the games,
and frequently applauded the good plays
made.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1896-04-02/ed-1/?sp=13&q=Co-eds+Basket+Ball+Match+Basketball+Basket-ball+Teams+Team&st=text&r=-0.247,-0.075,1.494,1.494,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CO-EDS AT BASKET BALL
Secret Practice at Berkeley for
the Great Match on
Saturday.
Greek Letter Fraternities to Present
Plays Paul Revere Lodge
Was Honored.
BERKELEY, Cal., April I.— The Berke
ley Co-ed basket-ball team are ready for
their battle with the Stanford nine next
I Saturday. They have gone into secret
practice and are devoting their time and i
i attention to signal work and to giving
their muscles the hnal course of ex
ercise before they stand up against
the wearers of the cardinal. They
are ail on the gui vive, as are
j the other women athletes of the
i university, for the contest on Saturday
will be t*e first contest they have entered
for honors. "We have the reputation and
the athletic prestige of the university to
uphold," said one of the fairest members
of the team to-day, "and we are going into
1 the struggle with* the purpose of coming
i out victors. We realize the odds we will
have to contend against in not being in as
I good training as we might, and then the
Stanford girls are much more experienced
than we. At any rate we will do our best,
J since we have accepted Stanford's chal
i lenge."
Two or three of the young women have
the appearance of being overtrained,
judging from their pallid faces and worn
expression. This may be due, however, to
anxiety over the result of the came. Tlieir
new costumes consist of white sweaters
and blue bloomers with gold trimmings.
University Cotillon.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
  	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063615/1898-12-18/ed-1/?sp=18&q=Basket+Ball+Basketball+Game+K+U+Naismith+Sport+Team&st=text&r=-0.248,-0.075,1.495,1.495,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BASKET BALL AT I U.
XKW BAJIE I.. CHKlT FA VII IX IX TUB
CLASSIC SHADES OF LA1VIIEACU.
How It I Plajeil The Tennis That
Ilnie Hern Formed The Fncnlty
Eiijoj- Ihe Game Clinncellur
Snow a. Crack Plnjer.
LAWRENCE. KAS.. Dec. 17.-(SpeciaU
The basket ball "fever" has broken out
In Its most violent form among Kansas
university people. Dr. Naismith. the new
physical director, brought the germs with
him, and that they were healthy specimens
is evidenced by their activity.
At first only a few of the students siw
in basket ball the diversion. But the dis
ease spread rapidly. Not only doe- eai h
class already possess its basket ball team,
but the literary and the scientific men of
the faculty are backing their "crack fives.
Eve-ry evening the gymnasium is filled with
a scrambling mass of humanity, and the
spectators who can recognlz. a friend or
acquaintance In the melee must be gifterd
with second sight.
Five men compose a team at basket ball.
The floor Is divided into three parts. Tho
center men of the plaving teams oe-upy a
space chalked off in the middle, am, the
other four dispose themselves In various
graceful attitudes in the end sections. The
referee tosses up the ball just above the
heads of the centers, who are standing
face to face. Each makes a jump and en
deavors to hit the hall, knocking it over
to his own men and toward his goal. Then,
the scramble begins. The accomplished,
and gentlemanly contortionist in the pat
ent medicine show could not rival basket
ball players In the way of tying French
knots in their corporal systems. The ma.-s
of writhing humanity turns over and over
in kaleidoscopic fashion, suddenly un
winds itself and is again resolved Into
parts. A man goes diving after the ball
and comos triumphantly up out of the
fray with his arms full of another man's
head! The aim In playing basket ball, so
it Is claimed. Is to throw the ball Into tho
round baskets, suspended at each end ot
the field, a greater number of times than
the opposing players. In reality, however,
it would seem that the cherls-hed object of
each plajer was to make as large and
choice collection of hruises as possible.
But that is basket ball from the specta
tor's point of view. To the players It Is
an all absorbing sport. Some of them
even have the audacity to assert that It Isi
a "gentle game, don't you know." Gentle,
indeed! One might as appropriately speak
of a bucking broncho as "well-mannered."
When the field Is not divided into sec
tions the game is reallr rough, but If thi
chalk lines are drawn, and fouls are faith
fully called whenever a man over-teps.
his boundaries, the bruise hunter adds to
Ills collection more slowly. It Is amusing:
to watch the players trying to remember
to have the proper respect for the bound
aries. Indeed It is truly pathetic to sej
what limitations of power a simple chalk
line can put on thee great, strong athletes.
In actual agony they har.g over the edge
and reach out helpless, longing arms to
ward the ball. Now and then an unruly
foot goes across the line, and then the
sharp whistle of the referee Is heard. A
foul entitles the players ort the otht.r side
a chance at throwing goal.
The game consists of two halves of
twenty minutes each. A twenty minute
rest is given between, and a new- team
put on to utilize the rest time. Each time
the ball goes Into the basket two points
are scored for the side whose goal Is
thrown As In baseball, a small score
Indicates a good game.
The Inventor of Ilnsket Hnll.
Dr. James Naismith Is the inventor of
basket ball. Unlike most of our games It
Is not the development of some medieval
sport. It was worked out on scientific
principles to meet a long felt want. Dr.
Naismith was physical director of a Y.
31. C. A. training school at Springfield.
Mass.. where the problem of supplying thlsj
need was brought to him for solution.
Busket ball was the result. It was In the
winter of 9I-52 that the game was intro
duced. The rules were made out and hung
In the "gym" fdr the inspection of playerj
before the game was ever tried. The men
were a little skeptical "at first about it.
but after the; ball was once thrown up no
coaxing was needed to Induce them to
Play. Basket ball came Into general favor
first through the Y. M. C. A. Having been
Introduced through the association it was
natural that it should spread through that
medium. Before long, however, colleges be
gan to investigate and adopt the game, ami
In the short .-pace of seven yeirs It has
gaimd a wide iopuhirlty. In the Eastern
colleges, both for men anil for womn.
basket ball Is the reigning favorite among
sports. The rules are not changed for tho
young women players, though doubtless the
game is played with a bit more tenderness.
Though at first sight the game appears
to be a free for all scramble. It soon be
comes evident that a number of sclentiilr?
,1'laya are iossibIe. Unfailing good judg
ment, anu goon muscular control are the
first requisites for a good player. The treat
ment of the ball Is the subject of several
rules. It can be tossed, rolled on Ihe floor
and pushed around, but must never In
kicked. There are no signals, and a play
lasts until the ball Is passed Into the basket.
Tennis In the 1'iilverslt jr.
The Kansas university men are going to
be great basket ball enthusiasts. Each
class has a picked team, and places on thei
teams are as much sought as on the var
sity eleven. Among faculty members thero
are two teams the Snow hall and tho
Frazer hall, representing the scientists and
the literary men. On the former team
Dr. WHHston. Marshall Barber. Clarenco
McClung. A. H. Clark and Dr. Naismith
hold positions. Their opponents are A.
G. Cantield. AY. H. Carruth. E. M. Hop
kins. M. W. Sterling and Archie Hogg.
On Tuesdays and Thursdays at 3 p. m. thesj
distinguished individuals lay aside their
dignity and their collars, don sweaters anil
pugilistic airs, and come forth into the
arena to dw battle. With a grace that
is acciuired only through long years of
bending over desks and laboratory tables,
they scamiier now here, now there, after
the elusive canvas sphere.
When the faculty teams met for their
last practice. Chancellor Snow- appeared.
He was Immediately besieged to play. The
chancellor protested that he was too green,
but such fetching invitations could never
be turned dotvn. The head of the universi
ty disappeared Into a dressing room, and
In a few moments, he emerged In a cos
tume of which the most noticeable feat
ures were- white canvas shoes, a seraphic:
grin, and a neutral tinted sweater. With
characteristic vigor he attacked the game,
and before long he was the champion play
er. There is nothing slow about the chan
cellor when he gets into action.
Tournament in January.
On January 13 an Indoor tournament will
be given. Basket hall will be the chief
feature of the c-xhihltlon. The old skat
ing rink on Kentucky street will probably
be rented for the occasion. Dr. Naismltii
says he enjoys working with college men
far better than with others. He believes
there is no artificiality whatever about e-ol-Iege
students. "If a man is a man they
will respect him and his endeavors in their
behalf." he says, "but they won t Stan. I
trilling a minute. When I find it yo'ing
fellow who kicks on the referee's decision-..
I just ask him n call fouls for a few mo
ments. After he has called a few and other
men have kicked on his rulings, h,. never
kicks again."
Pr. Naismith has much influence t
the young men in his charge. In Mrs. Cora
McColli,m Smith he has an able colleague.
The revolution In feeling which a few yearn
have brought about among the physical
culture students Is remarkable. When the
training was first Introduced about four
years ago and the girls lirst donned their
suits, the presence of a man within a ra
dius of three blocks wrought the most
awful consternation. Now men pass back
and forth throuch the r-vm to and from
the laboratory during the girls" cla.-aes and
ni'liing is thought ot it. Before long :hi
g.rls will trv basket ball. too. Equal suf
frage in ainietirs is one oi me cnarms of
Kansas university. Visitors to Lan-rem-o
must get a basket ball guide beforehand and
lecrn tne nngo. it tney wis.i to dd able to
converse intelligently with university peo
nle. for that is the all absorbing rnnle re
the day. It may not be a great while. Judg-
i hi; iruiii uiijjemuiii e ueioic processors
will be whistling students down in their
recitations and -allInc "foul" when thir
make mistakes in their translations, so
jreai is cue iiiuiience oi iiaoit
ADELIA ALICE Hl'MjPIUlEY.
There Is a boy now In an ncniltmlc grade
"r.l,." n'h, ..'III I... til..
.1. i ytj i.iuuai'i) oecjome
either a lawyer or a newspaper) man. At
tne close ot a. ie-soii in grammar a Tew
days since, the teacher was explaining the
new work for tho next day. a', studv of
word forms in gender. Turning to "this
bov. he said: "Now. what vvoulil yon call
the remlnine of stag?" Like- a flush came
ihe replj, "An afternoon tea." Brooklyn
Life.
A</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1903-09-20/ed-1/?sp=24&q=High+School+Girls+Illustrating+Play+Basket+Ball</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053934/1904-11-19/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Rules+Basketball+Basket+Ball+Dribble&st=text&r=-0.149,-0.015,1.297,1.297,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NEW RULES ON BASKETBALL
Changed Conditions For Championship
Contests.
Up to the present the basketball
rules have been amended each season
by additions and omissions in various
places. This year, however, the rules
have been rearranged and many rules
bear different numbers and are not
found in the same successive order.
An advantage in the new rule book
also is that at the top of the page i3
the page, so that it is no longer neccs-
indicated the rule number printed on
that page, so that it is no longer ne
cessary to turn back or forth to ascer
tain which rule is being read.
The first new feature is that the
rules became effective Nov. 1, 1904.
This settled a fixed time for everywhere
and did not leave it open for teams to
play old Ule3 because "they did not
have the new book and there is noth
ing in the rules saying when they be
come effective," In referring to the
basket, the word "basket" is not used
in contradiction to "goal."
The minimum size of playing space
(2,400 square feet) is omitted in rule 1.
section 1. Rule 3, section 1, requires
a background of wood at least three
quarters of an inch thick for the bas
kets. Screens are no longer permitted.
The paying of the officials expenses in
serial championship games is no longer
mandatory.
An important change in rule 11, sec
tion 10. prohibits more than one player
of each team from tackling the ball at
the same time. A "dribble" is now
only counted such when the player ad
vances more than two steps wtiile roll-
UDUDDDDGBD
You can eat anything, digest it and
enjoy it if you give your stomach a
thorough course of treatment with
Dr. laber's Pbpsin lompouna.
Perhaps your stomach is over
worked and accumulates undigest
ed matter whici ferments and up
sets the entire system, causing
belching and bloating, bad breath,
a languid, weary feeling, sleep
lessness, etc.
T&ESER'SIEEEMMlGOrJlFOUnD
cleans out the refuse, heals the irritated secretive linings of the stomach, stim
ulates an activity of the digestive fluids and tones up the entire tract. Blood is
pure when digestion is complete. Dr. Taber's Pepsin Compound produces
perfect, healthy digestion. 9
TABLETS, 10c, 25c, 50c. at drug stores. Uquld Form, 50c. and $1.
KTKZPMTK? To prove its merits, we will send sample
m mmwtmmm package by mail. Free, to any address.
DR. TABER MFG. CO., Poorto, Ills.
ing or bouncing the ball.
The rule that in a dribble both hands
shall not be used simultaneously more
than once is still effective. Under rule
11, section 17, a man is not out of
bounds if only one foot is outside.
Players may be changed at any time
during the game (new rule 1, section
26). Last year's rules as well as the
new rules authorizes the referee to
award one point to the man fouled by
an opponent while trying for goal.
There was some doubt formerly as to
whether the team whose player was
fouled should also have a free throw
for goal.
The uew rules add that "this shall
noi interfere with a free throw for goal
from foul line," thus making It pos
sible to secure four points on this olio
play, if while being fouled the player
throws the goal, two points are scored,
oue point is awarded by the nfere
aud the ilayer is allowed an additional
free throw for the foul giving him uu
opiiortunity of scoring one point moro
if he throws the foul goal.
Under the old rules if a player threw
for goal from outside and missed thu
basket the ball went to the center,
while under the new rules the ball con
tinues to play. r
Under rule 12, section 1 and 4. tho
referee is required to promptly dis
qualify any player using profane or
abusive language.
FELIRN EIII</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99021999/1907-02-24/ed-1/?sp=30&q=College+Athletes+William+Lush+Basket+Base+Ball+Sport+Game+Basketball&st=text&r=-0.223,-0.072,1.446,1.446,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WITfl COLLEGE ATHLETES
Doinei ia tha Field of 8port in Eatt tod
Watt.
SITUATION IN THE MIDDLE WEST
Vbal William Lak, Tale Baa Ball
Coach, Thinks f Basket Bail
Flea far Kacalaa; later-eolleg-latc
"port.
CoIIprs banket ball being a Sme that
tin coma to atay. It la only tha part of
araclouaneaa to take tba pm at tba valu
ation that baa been put upon It bjr moat
tollps rnen and admit that tbera ara rea
son for Ita popularity. Only a while ago
It was very much the fashion to sneer at
the same and say thnt it was a girl s
game and tha like. A short view of a fast
fame of basket ball Is enough to convlnoe
anyone that, whatever else it may be, it
Is not a girl s game when college men
ylay It.
The aonr.twhat tardy recognition of the
endurance and speed giving qualities of
the game by college coaches now la be
ginning to arrive. Man who looked at the
game once with fear because It w.n lm
jf adding another to what they cmlclred
too large a list of aporta now ara this
to sea that It has its place In the winter
eaaon for helping to develop men for
the spring outdoor cimpaVn In many
porta.
Billy Lnsh mm Basket Ball.
For a general all round eulogy of the
game It would be linrJe to find anything
more complete than tho utterances of
William Iiush, the former Cleveland baae
ball player, who la In charge cf the base
ball team at Tale. It covers the subject
ao well that It la worth wnile quoting at
length. Bomeone waa talking to Luah out
In Bt. Paul when 'he Title basket ball
team waa there awhile fro nnd thla Is what
the baae ball coach bad to aay about basket
ball:
"Of the various bransnes of college sport
that go to fill up tbe interim between rhe
foot ball and baae aall naaaom all have
gradually given way before basket ball
until It now atanda as the most popular
winter sport among the colleges aa well
as the most useful and benoflclal, both for
men who are training for one of tha major
sports and for those whose sole r art ..In
college athletics la plav.d on the gym
nasium floor In thla branch.
"For ten yeara or more It haa been
growing gradually in college favor and
even without the forward pasa of the foot
ball field to throw it Into still brighter
relief the game was sure to win Its way
on the merits of Its play. The qualities It
demands and those It develops were enough
In themselves to Insure ultimata favor, but
the play of the last few yeara in the Inter
collegiate banket ball league, together with
the audden prominence which the grafting
of ita forward pass on the fot ball tulea
has given It, placea basket ball far ahead
of the position It held In former yenra
and gives an added Importance to the play
of thla aeason, both Inside and outside the
league.
What It Develops.
"Among tha qualities developed In the
men who take It up seriously are coolness,
decision, auppleneas, activity and team
play. Weight, height and auperlor strength
are advantageous, but with the exception
of the center position, where height Is a
requisite, there is no special premium put
upon any of theae qualities. Speed and
agility are the qualities most desirable.
After them come endurance and the ability
to submerge self In order to play for and
with the team. The new man at the game
Is apt to be 'all nerves.' He passes too
quickly, worka too hard, and when he gets
a chance to shoot for a goal he Invariably
doea It too quickly, with tbe result that his
try misses, where an Instant's hesitation
for poise and aim would have converted
bis worthless try Into a valuable goal.
"It Is disconcerting to know that one
man on the other team Is specially placed
to guard' him and the knowledge that he
Is ever near and trying his utmost to In
tercept the shot gives a green man the
rattles' as quickly as anything could.
"The veteran haa learned his lesson and
Newsy Gossip
Don't turn corners on the wrong side of
the road.
Buffalo people spent $2,000,000 on automo
biles last year.
Lanolins will speedily clean bands soiled
by work about a car.
It la estimated that between 1.000 and
1.6ot American tourists wlU take cars
abroad this year.
An automobile to be run by springs, like
a clock, Is the invention of two Schenec
tady, N. Y., men.
One tire maker is out with a written
guarantee that his Urea will give tba buyer
(.M) miles of wear.
The kaiser has selected June 14 as the
date for ths emperor's cup race, which be
will attend in person.
The Jim Crow automobile line started by
negros of Nashville, Tenn., haa been f l-n-doned,
as unprofitable.
Efforts are being made to make the Boa
ton show, March toe greatest New
Uugland ever Las suen.
The French Chamber of Deputies haa
voted down a bill to tax foreign automo
biles touring In Franoe.
A conservative estimate of the automobile
business done in Baltimore In luo puts tUe
total of sales at la,uu0,uuu,
Philadelphia now wants a building as big
aa the Cltioago Coliseum to aooouiiuudaie
Its next automobile siiuw.
Beversi manufacturers ara producing rua
a bouts for two persons with aa extra rum
ble seat for the chauffeur.
Automoblllng is on the Increase In Egypt,
where One roads can be bulli on tke Ueaeri
at a oust of not over 110 per tulle.
Hlgh-powsred runabouts Instead of nv
tot cycles may be adopted by the Uelrolt
police department fur its dyiug squad.
President Kooasvell has wade an engage
ment witu a well known vnauiieur ior a
tour of Washington's atresia by sight.
The Chicago snow "this ysar took Its plaoe
as a social occasion wltn the horse snow
and the (ashiouaule charitable events.
Ovsr ISO, (Mi worth of space la the show
to be held In Luu.ueene Garden. PttUuurg.
In April, already baa Ima oootracted
for.
Owing to the opposition of tbe legislator
the project of Ute Uaua-stata highway lit
Pennsylvania is discouraging, this year, at
least.
Only T.O00 square feet of the apace aet
aside for aa automobile exhibit at tha
Jameetown exposition remains to be al
lotted, Chicago's great show was threatened with
destruction by a lira which wrecked an
automobile agency in tha rear of the Coli
seum. It no longer is necessary tor a motorist
to be a club member to Join a state or
ganisation of the American Automobile as
sociation. Some Z.0OO members ef the National As
sociation of liiMtdmakers will hold their
annual convection at Pittsburg on MaroA
U and U.
R. A. Parker, an attorney Interested la
ths legal battle over the Bsideo patent, es
timates that I10u.0uu,0uv la at stake lu the
litigation.
Bieermg arms on some motor oars re
cently purchased by the government were
required to wilhsland a bending pressure
of five tons.
So sharp waa the rivalry over tbe allot
ment of space for the Paris salon that
there la talk of aa Independent aocessory
how asxt year.
Berlin will spend $11,000 la experimenting
with automobile fire engines. If auocaaaful
horses, which cost the city ttt.MD a year,
WlU be abandoned,
A mixture of alcohol and hydrocarbons
has recently been produced In Germany
which la fully equal to gasoline la point
C nargy and laAaiuiuabUttjr and Which oaa
with the pasa of the ball has vised up the
altuatlon. Aa he catches It he knows how
near his guard la and whether tie must
hurry the shot or can take time to aim.
If he haa an Instant for preparation the
try seldom falls, a; d It Is by reason of
that ooolness which enables him to decide
In advance, that he Is so much more valua
ble than some other man who may be able
to do many ether things better, but who
lacka his experience. The gsme develops
this quality and teaches ths players In
stinctively to decide and to act In unison.
"Ruppleness and activity are developed
as in no other game, since every muscle
of the body Is called Into play and every
move must be quick If It Is to be effective.
The moves of foot ball are often alow and
penderoua, calling for strength to repel
or to urge on an attack, and the actual
period of play In two thirty-minute halves
has been found to be less than fifteen min
utes. Excels Base) Ball.
"In baae ball quick action la demanded
spasmodically, while at least half the time
Is spent in idleness and rest on the bench.
Hockey demands considerable action, but
It relates more to the legs than to any
other part of the body, and continued skat
ing serves to harden muscles that should
be aoft to be of most service to tbe base
bell or foot ball player.
"Basket ball, on the other hand, develops
all parts of the body equally. From the
blowing of the whistle at the start of the
contest there is scarcely a pause until the
end of the half. During two periods of
twenty minutes each there Is seldom more
than a quarter of an hour taken out for
all delays and pauses, leaving twenty-five
minutes of actual play, during which every
man i not only moving, but is working
faster than the foot ball player running,
dodging, catching, passing trying by every
fair method In his power to outwit, outpfay
or wear down the opponent who is specially
opposed to him.
"It is constant and quirk action for every
muscle of the body, since the possibilities
of the game call them all Into service
sooner or later. A game for the email man
aa well as the big one. It develops the same
traits in both. Except for the extra
strength of the big man. which sometimes
enables him to outlast the smaller, there
is no advantage In Ms power.
"In basket ball the star man Is usually
the one who knows how to help his team
In the most effective manner rather than
the man who stands alone nnd trusts to the
power of the other members of his five to
give him a chance to shine. The man wh
is not a team man has no rdare In basket
ball and he soon learns his lemon or Is
dropped from the squad.
Team Work Counts.
"The Vne for all' spirit Is stronger In
this sport than In any other and surpasses
even foot ball In Its requirement for team
handling of the ball. On the gridiron one
can do things by himself and win for hie
team. A drop kick, a long run or any one
of a number of 'one man' plays may result
in a foot ball score.
"In basket ball It Is expressly forbidden.
A man may be a marvelous dribbler and
be able to take the ball In this manner
from one end of the floor to the other, but
it Is Impossible for him to do more, aa tha
rules provide that he has no right to try
ror a score arter dribbling, but must pass
to some teammate. The result Is that the
ball must always be handled by more than
one man almost always by more than two.
Generally all Ave men are In the play and
under these conditions the team Is doing Its
best work.
"Orlfllths, captain of Harvard last year,
and Kelnath of Pennsylvania, were won
derful dribblers, and earJh often tpok the
balr- the entire length of the floor by him
self. But the rest of the team was al
ways busy while one of them was doing
this, with the result that when he had to
pasa the other four men were In position
which had been carefully worked out In
advance, and every man on the team gen
erally knew to whom and at what appt tbe
pass would be made. Both men were In
valuable to their teama, but both were
essentially team play men.
"The coaches of crack teams have real
ised the value of basket ball as a training
for long distance runners and for Jumpers
and have sent candidates Into the sport
each year. The amount of endurance
gained on the basket ball floor can be
compared only to that of hockoy, whll
the advantage between these two as a
track developer lies entirely with basket
for Owners of
be directly used In motors built to con
sume gasoline.
By promoting mammoth meets, runs and
tours the Chicago Automobile club has
grown to rank perhaps second only to the
New York organisation.
Beat tie's postmaster has asked the Post
office department for an appropriation to
permit hlin to experiment with motor cars
In the collection of mall.
Tnranantr, 1.S I.
Rockefeller of Japan," who is touring the
United States, recently ordered a fifty
ywwv, Aiuinvu car.
In place of a show the Association of
German Automobile Manufacturers will
hold a series of contests for freight ve
hicles, motor busses and motor cabs.
An Ohio town baa framed a municipal law
forbidding wheelmen to cling to a passing
automobile, and making the automobile
driver liable to a fine If he permits it.
Thirty liters of gasoline for every 100 kilo
meters of distance constitutes the new and
principal clause in the regulations for
tills year's Orand Prix race in Franca.
Popular opposition has kUled the ordi
nance Introduced In the city council at
Nashville, Tenn., prohibiting running of
machines by persons under 21 years of
ge.
An English whsel which Is said to give
satiafactlou is covered with a solid tire
of pigskin, road shocks being absorbed by
a sort of ball-bearing arrangement at the
bub.
Soap, graphite, stiff tallow or red lead
mixed with glycerine are all good for
stopping leaks In the unions of the fuel
pipe. The threads should be liberally
smeared.
That all automobile buyers are rich Is
a fallacy which becomes more apparent as
such each year. The use of motor cars
is spreading rapidly among those of mod
erate Incomes.
Many motor-driven, high-wheeled bug
gies are being used among farmers In
localities in westsrn states where the roads
ara not ail that could be desired for horse
drawn vehicles. S
Greater attsntlon Is paid this year by
purchasers to the braking capacity of the
various types on ths market, and In many
oases poor brakes have been the cause of
ths loss ef sales.
New Castle county, Delaware, has made
a bid for automoblilng by asking the leg
islature to permit It to borrow $Wi3o
with which to build substantial permanent
roads within its borders.
Thome A. Edison, whose relationship to
automobiles Is known on account of his
electric battery. Is to be honored in France
with an 'electric play," embracing the
principal episodes la his life.
Aluminum castings were such a rarity
a few years ago that an order for a few
hundred pound was considered a big one.
Now several automobile builders each are
using l.uuo,yuO pounds a year.
To maks them more prominent in Lon
don s crowded streets automobile ambu
lances are painted white with large red
Geneva croasea. They carry pennant fly
ing from the peaks of the canopies.
Aa automobile omnibus company of
Cairo, Kgypu Is operating four automo
biles and soon will put on mora. Auto
mobiles also are being used by the Kgyp-
strvlceOVnimttt ln 'olic Ihspictloa
It practically baa been determined that
the feature of the 1J Orruond-Daytoun
Ileach tournament will be a tuw-mlle oon
teet. run la two lM-uule relays, for a gold
Ping orlvarf"" vrSMn ot win-
Th following have been appointed to serve
on the racing board of the American Au
tonoblle association for 1W7: Wiluam K.
Vandebilt, Jr. Buse.ll ThomsT Dave
lieiutea Morris, A. H, Pardingion, Frank
ball since It employs ths ssme set ft
muscles that Is used In track work, -hill
hockey Is Inclined to develop others.
Tralalaa; far Bass Ball.
"Base ball coaches are also beginning
tp see the advantage In the game. Men
who are good players are made still better
by reason of basket ball play, and it
etands to reason that this should be so.
The long free swing of the arm that Is
used In panning the ball acts as a con
tinual exerciser for the throwing arm and
keepa It free from klnka during the months
that base ball Is out of the question.
"Nor Is It only the throwing arm that
get a benefit. The entire body is trained
and the quick poise and balance that are
learned on the basket ball floor become
more valuable assets to a candidate for
the nine, who must move outckly. gathfr
In the ball, recover his po'ae and thrpw
the ball to some one else In the shortest
possible time.
"Feet and hands often refuse to "move
together In this kind of work, and the
l"tlnrtlre ability M1
rlnver ncoitlr to receive the ball in many
different r-oplttnna and etni to keen h's
balance often helps him when he ias to
hnl th rne"er hnV on the diamond.
"Since the adoption of the forward paee
by the foot ball rule mawers the minor
sport has acquired a new prominence, and
for the delivery and handling of long passes
In foot ball there can be no better training
field than the basket ball floor, where long
passes ate constantly being made and where
tha perfect hamlllnff of them la not only
desirable, but essential.
"A number of other examples might be
cited where "foot ball haa been benefited by
basket ball training, but the fact Is too
well accepted to require It. With none ef
the corollary advantages which It holds by
reason of Its relations to other branches,
bssket ball would still be a good enough
snort to stand on the merits of Its own
play. But ss It Is with the advantages
It holds ss a helper In other lines of ath
letic activity It Is not to he wondered at
that Its stride Into favor among the ath
letes as welt aa spectators Is being rapidly
lengthened."
All of which, as a side tight, may be
taken to explain why Gllmore Kinney,
captain of the Tale base ball team. Is play
ing basket ball this season, although there
was violent objection to his doing the same
last year. Kinney was kept oft the basket
bail five last year.
Chicago Worries Rarly.
Leo de Tray, captain of the University
of Chicago foot ball team. Is worried over
the general outlook. He does not know
whether his team la going to be able to play
Michigan next fall and he doea not know
whether he himself aa well as some other
men who are counted on for the Chicago
eleven will be qualified to play next fall.
De Tray haa found that there Is a wide
diversity, of opinion among the men In the
university, aa well aa among the deana of
some of the achools, as to what the terms
of the rules demand.
Chicago has raised Its scholarship stand
ing much higher In the last few months.
Several of the best athletes have been
dropped and others are In fear of like treat
ment. Some of the best students In the
athlstto squsd are In fear of the new se
verity. It Is now a rule that each student
who takes part In athletics must take three
courses, which will Insure his graduating
In four years.</text>
      </result>
      <result>

  </topic>
</topics>
