<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-jim-thorpe</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1912-07-08/ed-1/?sp=1&q=THORPE+Olympic&st=text&r=0.171,0.32,1.364,1.386,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THORPE WINS PENTATHLON
Americans Show Up Impressive*}
ly in 800-Metre and Running
High Jump Trials, but
Fall Down in 10-000-
Metre Heats,
4

Thorpe an Eaay Victor.
Only one other number on the pro*
gramme was concluded to-day. Tha*,
was the pentathlon, which was intendej
to be a test of all around prowesj,
When thia event was Included in the
Olympic games conservative oldtlmers,
both Kngllsh and Americans, who here*
tofore had domlnated the fleld sports. re
garded it with lUBptcton as a trick oj
the newcomers to galn polnts whlch were
not contemplated ln the orlginal pro*
gramme.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045487/1912-07-16/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Thorpe+James+Olympic+THORPE</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THORPE IS BEST ATHLETE
Stadium, Stockholm, Sweden,
July.16 America has again beat
en the world in athletic competi
tion.
When James Thorpe, Carlisle
Indian, won he decthalon yester
day afternoon, adding six more
points to-the' Yankee total and
closing the track and' field section
of the Olympic meet, the Ameri
cans had won by a larger margin
than in any previous internation
al meet."
Thorpe has proven himself the
best all-around athlete in the
world, winning both the pentha
lon and decthalon.
America scored 128 -points in
all events', including riding, shoot
ing, swimming and fe'ncing, the
nearest rival being Sweden, with
104. In the purely athletic con-</text>
      </result>
    </results>

        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1913-01-28/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Thorpe+James+Olympic+THORPE+JAMES&st=text&r=-0.247,-0.075,1.493,1.493,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>6
WORLD'S GREATEST ATHLETE IS DISCREDITED
JIM THORPE ADMITS PROFESSIONALISM
®+Q>
Confession Is a Matter of International Significance
i
All Indian's Olympiad Prizes Will Have to Be Returned
Touch of Pathos in His Letter
To A. A. U. Secretary; Did
Not Realize Wrong
He Was Doing
NEW YORK, Jan. 27.—James Thorpe, the Indian
athlete and Olympic champion, today admitted that the
charges of professionalism brought against him were
true and formally retired from amateur athletics.
Thorpe's confession was contained in a letter to the reg
istratiotl committee of the Amateur Athletic union,
which met today to investigate his C_#e.
The letter admitted that Thorpe had played baseball
for a salary on a professional team three years ago while
a student of the Carlisle Indian school, but said that on
the same team there were several northern college men
who were regarded as amateurs and Thorpe did not
realize his participation was wrong. Thorpe added that
he did not play for the money he earned, but for the
love of the game.
Thorpe's winning of the pentathlon and decathlon
events of the Olympic games in Stockholm, and later
his wonderful performances which won for him the all
id championship of the A. A. U. at Celtic park last
September, had stamped him the most marvelous all
round athlete of modern times. In addition his
as a football player had earned for him last season, by
unanimous choice of leading sporting writers the posi
tion of half back on the all American football team for
1912.
LOS ANGELES MAN MOVES UP
All the prizes and the honors which Thorpe had
gained since 1909—the date from which his standing as
a professional begins—must be transferred, through the
officials of the Amateur Athletic union, to the men who
finished second to the Indian in every event. This will
mean that the trophies and points won in the pentathlon
and decathlon must be given, respectively, to F. R. Bie,
Norway, and 11. Wieslander, Sweden, and that Donahue
of California and Lomberg of Sweden will take second
places. John Bredemus of Princeton finished second to
Thorpe in the American all round championship, and
Bruno Brodd of the Irish-American Athletic club third,
and they therefore now must be accorded the honors.
In this championship Thorpe made a total score of 7.476
points and broke the former record of Martin Sheridan
by 91 points.
UNITED STATES STILL HOLDS LEAD
The loss of the six points scored by Thorpe in the
Olympic games still leaves the United States winner by
a wide margin, however, the total standing, United
States 79, with Finland in second place with 29.
Charges that Thorpe had played professional base
ball in Winston-Salem. X. C, first were published last
week in a Worcester (Mass.) newspaper. Tames E. Sulli
van, the secretary, and other officials of the Amateur
Athletic union immediately began an investigation, which
culminated today in a meeting of the officials of the
A. A. U. and the Amercan Olympic committee in this
city. Those in attendance v.*ere Gustavus T. Kirby,
president of the A. A. U. and vice president of the
American Olympic committee; James E. Sullivan, secre
tary, and Bartow S. Weeks of the registration com
mittee of the A. A. U. and vice president of the Olympic
committee.
Prior to the meeting, Glenn S. Warner, athletic
director of the Carlisle Indian school, called on Mr.
Sullivan and presented to him Thorpe's confession of
professionalism and letter expressing the regret of M.
Friedman, superintendent of the Carlisle school, that
his premier athlete was guilty as charged.
PLAYED FOR LOVE OF GAME
Thorpe's letter, dated in Carlisle, Pa., yesterday, and
addressed to Mr. Sullivan, follows:
"When the interview with Mr. Clancy, stating that I
had played baseball on the Winston-Salem team, was"
shown me. I told Mr. Warner that it was not true, and,
in fact, 1 did not play on that team. But so much has
been said in the papers since then that I went to the
school authorities this morning and told them just what
there was in the stories.
"I played baseball in Rocky Mount and in Fayette
villc, X. C, in the summer of 1909 and 1910, under my
own name. On the same teams I played with were
several college men from the north who were earning
money by hall playing during their vacations and who
were regarded as amateurs at home. I did not play for
the money there was in it, because my property brings
me in enough money to live on, but because 1 liked to
play baseball.
DID NOT REALIZE OFFENSE
"I was not very wise in the ways of the world and
did not realize this was wrong and it would make me
a professional in track sports, although I learned from
the other players that it would be better for me not to
let any one know that I was playing, and for that re-ison
I never told any one in the school about it until today.
"In the fall of 1911 I applied for readmission to this
00l and came back to continue my studies and take
part in the school sports, and, of course, I wanted to
get on the Olympic team and take the trip to Stock
holm. I had Mr. Warner send in my application for
registering in the A. A. U., after T had answered the
questions and signed it, and I received my card allowing
me to compete in the winter meets and other track
sports.
"I never realized until now what a big mistake I
made by keeping it a secret about my ball playing, and
I am sorry I did so. I hope I will be partly excused by
the fact that T was simply an Indian schoolboy and did
not know all about such things.
OTHER COLLEGE MEN DID IT
"In fact, I did not know that I was doing wrong,
because I was doing what I knew several other college
men had done, except that they did not use their own
names.
"I have always liked sports and only played or ran
races for the fun of the thing and never to earn money.
I have received offers amounting to thousands of dollars
since my victories la«t summer, but I have turned them
al! down because I did not care to make money from my
athletic skill. I am \ery sorry, Mr. Sullivan, to have it
all spoiled in this way, and I hope the Amateur Athletic
union and the people will not be too hard in judging me.
"Yours truly,
"JAMES THORPE."
Mr. Friedman in his* letter says that neither the
faculty of the Carlisle Indian school nor Athletic
Director Warner had knowledge of Thorpe's profession
alism and declares the confession has brought gloom to
the entire institution.
INEXPERIENCE SOME EXCUSE
The committee which met today to investigate the
charges against Thorpe, after having read the confession
o- tne athlete, issued a statement in effect that Thorpe
was selected as a member of the Olympic team without
Two Polo Matches Today
On Crossways
BURLINGAME. Jan. 27. —Tomorrow
afternoon at 3 o'clock, on the Crossways
field, there will be a polo match between
two picked teams. One ot them, known
as the Kamnainas, will be captained by
Walter Dillingham, the noted Hawaiian
polo player. The other team, known as
the Malahinis, will be captained by Tom
l>riscoll. It will be a four period match
and will be played in honor of Mrs. Wal
ler Dillingham, who is expected to ar
_t Kurlingame today. After this
there will be a practice match of
cix periods.
the least suspicion of his ever having been a professional.
They justify in some measure Thorpe's position by say
ing it should be noted that he is an Indian, of limited
experience and education, and lacking in the knowledge
of other than bis own people.
The statement .-ays that, while Thorpe is deserving
of the severest condemnation for concealing the fact
that he had played professional baseball, the committee
feels that those who knew of Ids professions*] acts are
deserving of still greater censure for their silence. The
Amateur Athletic union announces that it will do every
thing in its power to insure the return of prizes and the
readjustment of points won by Thorpe and will imme
diately eliminate the records from its books.
In the pentathlon in Stockholm Thorpe finished first
in the running broad jump, first in the 200 meters run,
first in the 1,500 meters run and third in the javelin
event. In the decathlon, which consisted of the 100
meters dash, running broad jump, shot put, running high
jump, 40*1 meter*- run. 110 meters hurdle, discus throwing,
pole vault, javelfh throw and 1.500 meters run, Thorpe
had a percentage of 8,412.955 against 7,724.495' by Wies
lander, Sweden, his nearest opponent.
HIS REMARKABLE RISE
James Thorpe, a Sac and Fox Indian, first was heard
of several years ago as a football player with the Car
lisle team. Later he specialized in weight throwing,
jumping and running. He also became noted as a la
crosse and baseball player, and in the latter branch of
sport several of the major league teams have tried to
procure his services. Only last year it was stated that
Pittsburg and Washington, endeavored to secure him,
but the Indian refused to sign a contract, declaring that
he wished to remain an amateur.
After the Olympic games in Sweden last year, King
Gustave sent for Thorpe to congratulate him on his
prowess. At first the Indian timidly declined to meet
the monarch, but later, when several of the American
committeemen insisted that he do so, Thorpe went to
the palace. There the king took the Indian by the hand
and smilingly said:
"You are the greatest athlete in the world."
On his return to the United States from Sweden.
President Taft sent Thorpe a letter congratulating him
os his victories in the Olympic games.
Thorpe Refuses to Talk
CARLISLE, Pa., Jan. 27.—When seen in the Indian
school here James Thorpe declined to make any state
ment tonight concerning his admission of professionalism
and retirement as an amateur athlete.
He stated, however, that lie "might have something
to say tomorrow" and added:
"I must have time to consider my future plans."
Washington Park Soccer
Champions
ALAMEDA, Jan. 27.—The Interpark
Soccer league, the membership of
which is made up of boys, has closed
its season. The championship in the
heavy weight class has been awarded
to the Washington park team. In the
middleweight class the championship
went to the Lincoln park team and the
lightweight team from the same park
captured the championship in Its class.

RECEPTION BY COLLEGE -San RafMa, .Inn. 27.
The faculty and pupils of Dominican college
gave a reception Saturday afternoon iv houor
uf Right Uev. Edward F. Hauna D. D.
THE SAN FRANCISCO CALL, TUESDAY, JANUARY 28, 1913.
JAMES THORPE,</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1913-01-28/ed-1/?sp=14&q=THORPE+Olympic+James+OLYMPIC+Thorpe+Thorp</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THORPE
IN THESE AMATEUR DAYS
elr"
HfeffX'S A
3vArr6R.iorj,
V-Q UCH-iaJO
"TWat SwfTN ear
Oopy right. IM.I. by The Preat Publishing Co. (Tha New York Wot Id i.
Hcncs 3 oolias
MAKES EOLl CONFESSION
MOW
I
OLYMPIC HERO,
'J
0
THAT HE IS A PROFESSIONAL
BaW V. I 1 I I I as sgsv gar. aagPsU 1 T X
American Athletic Authorities Apologize to Swe
den and All Other Countries for Allowing
Indian to Compete at International
Games at Stockholm.
r
,IM TUOHHtfi'S 'onfmitloi! that he
protaagloual at UM tlai ho rompi'teil for the United Statei In (he la
lernetlunel amateur Olympic guinea at Stockholm laat amainier, la on
0t tie lilnNt aanaatloua In the hlttory
ta
tfca AmerUan Olympic Committee leeaons the force of Mi blow and In a
COLUMN
Thorpe won both Hie Decathlon
MOie IVntatbloii everita lu Hie meet at Sto kbolin and tkta Mi ned lor him
pratt from erery quarter of the gloh. The King of -live den upon ten
Wrlng Tcorpn the brome liuai fur winning the Pentathlon, aalj
"Tou.'alr. are the greateat athlete In the world.'
Thorpe alao wan presented a handiome Viking ahlp. the prize tendered
tap the Cur of lluaa'.a for winning
Daeatblon
Mot inly will thee pr.ees be taken
awmy from the Kos and Bar Indian, but
he'll have to return all the amateur
arteee Intruding the National A. A. U.
amplornIp, which he won tail fall.
Xt la now alao charged agel at Thnrpa
fM laat fall ha algned .tb the
Ptratee of the National gu i
play first baee for them ihla aeaion.
ey Dreyfuea, Prealdent or the leatn,
being a iked whether thle report
I true, refuted to make any slate
at HORPK tn lila confession declare!
that he didn't know It waa wrong
io ptey professional ban and oora-
feta tn amateur athletics at tha ea.ni
tskae. aa he aaya that there were eeveral
prominent college athlote dj'.ug
ama thing. An effort will be made to
Thorn tell tuat wbat oeilege men
played ball with, him. for the sooner thel
the amateur ranks are fraa nf aunti ath
letes the better It will be for thn mint.
The disqualification uf Thorpe makes
a alight diaerenoe In the standing or
the) nattona at the Olympic meat llow
eewr, It len t big enough to cauae Anier
lea to leas ths credit of winning first
When Thorpe returua hla Olympic i
prise, the Vlkltig ahlp will ba turned i
ear to II. Welslander of Hweden. who
sMahed eecond In the decathlon, and
P. R. Ble of Norwey. who finished aee
oad la the pentathlon, will receivs tba I
bast of the King of Bweden.
John Bredemue of I'rtncetou will alao
aasg by Thorpe' a dlegrac. aa ha On
lahag second to the great Carlisle ath
lete In the all-around champlonMilpe at
CaMo Park leet September. On that ic
eaaton the big redakln plied up 7,7(
getnta. a world', record.
The fret Intimation thut Tborpe wis
a profaaalonal run from Charlea
Clancy of eVtuthbtldge laat Thuraday.
Me declared that Thorpe played under
hat management tn the Carolina League
rat year ago. Tha following day he
denied tbe etory, eaylug he waa ml
qooced HU denial was hardly cold whan play
aJ sad umptree from other parts of
the eouaary came forward and 'aid that
the ha ow all the time tbat the Jim
Thorpe who played In tba Southern
sheer league and the athlete who car
Had oC tbe auprem honora abroad laat
auasscar were one and the earn. Be
fee the Amateur Athletic Union could
an announcement a to what they
In their 11.'eertgallon Into
Thorpe's oaae Qlen Warner, the Car
Kate aoach, oame her and handel tn
Jama E. OuBtvan, Secretary -Treasurer
of the A. A V., Thorpe's confession,
e
FTBK rial (Wring the matter for
am eeweral houra the A. A. U. office
gave out the following statement
The Team Selection Committee of
she American Olympic Committee
oeteeted Jem. a Thorpe as one of the
mombere of the A.:,rl-n Olympto
and did ao without the leaet
Helen aa to there having ever
any act of profaeiinnallem on
Thorp a part.
tr the paat eeveral yeara Thnrpa
ha beet) a member of the Carllale
Sdlan School, which la e inducted by
a Oovernment of the I'nltail Htatee
kt Carlisle, Pa., tnrough tha Indian
Ihapartmant of the Oapartment o! the
tat trior.
hfr, aiann Warner, fnernaely of
Cansall, a man whna reputation la
af the VaTbea: and a. nose a'-out a y
atatatament he nacer bean dnuhttwl,
haa been In charge nf tha athlatlii
eetlvlttaa of the Institution During
tha period of Mr Thurpa'e memoer
ahlp at Carllale he competed on Ha
gootball. haaehnll and track and field
htejna and represented It In Inter -exattaglate
and other ooataeta, all of
weiloli ware open only te amateura,
6 neither Oarlhila nor aay of the
Itutlone wttli which It compete
other than amateur teama
niorpe's ataiiding aa an amateur
had aever been itueetlonod, nor waa
aay proton ever made against him
ajar any statement ever made aa to
having practised with pro-
ix pi-ufrxjlotial and that ba at a
of ath Mia The prompt apology of
sportsmanlike nay even up the sit
uation TUo A. A. U. hare tu inaka an
announcamout to-day aa to Ita find
ing In Ita Investigation Into ftag
itatua of the Indian, and tbat ha
came forward himself and confessed
that ba la a profaaalonal makaa tbla
actluu unueceitary
Tborpa will he stripped or all tba
glory ba won on tba amateur Held
and that Include morn honor than
avor fell to the lot of any athlete In
tbo world, lie not only la a wonder
ful football and baaaball player, but
he can do all aorta of record-breaking
lunta In every titlmr lirnnch of aport.
feaelonala. lei a having played
with nr aa one of them
The wldeel possible publicity waa
given the team relented by the
American Olympic Committee, and
It eeema atrange that men having
knowledge of Mr. Thorpe'e profes
'lonal 'conduct did Bel at auah time
fnr the honor of their couiitry come
forward and place In tha hand of
the American committee auoh in
formation ae they had.
No euch Information waa given,
nor waa a tuggeitlon even made a
to Thorpe being other than the
emateur which ha was aupposed to
ba This country a of eueh tre
mendous territorial expanse, and the
alhletea taking part therein are eo
nugierous. that It Is sometimes ex
tremely difficult lo ascertain tha his
tory of an athlete's paat. In tha J
"eiiwn oi me American team tha
committee endeavored to use every
poaalbla precaution, and where there
was tha slightest doubt aa to a
man s amataur standing, hie entry
was not considered.
Thorpes act of profewtlonallam
was In a sport ovei whloh the Ama
teur Athletic Union haa no direct
control; it was at a member of a
baseball team In a minor league, and
In games which ware not reported
1 1 the Important papers of the coun
try. That he pitied under his own
name would give no direct notice
to any one concerned, aa there are
man- of hla name. The reaaon why
ha himself did not give notice or lit
acts Is explained by him on the
ground uf Ignorance. In some
.tust Ideation of this poalllon. It
should be noted thai Mr Thorpe Is
an Indian of limited experience and
education In the uava of othsr than
hla nwn people
The American o:.i mjilc Committee
and iho Amateur Athletic Union fee'
that while Mr. Thorpe la deaerv.ng
of the eecereat condemnation for con
cealing I lie fact that he had profes
riouallred lilmeeir by receiving money
for pitying baseball, they also feel
that lhos who knew of hla profwa
slona.1 nets are deserving of atlll
greiiter censure for their silence.
The American Olympic Comnililae
and the A ma tcir Athletic Tnlon
tender to the Hwedlsli Olympl 0 Com
inlitoe and thrumr.i tne International
Olympic CommllteH to the natlona of
the world. Ihlr apnlory for having
entered Mr. Thorpe and having per
mitted him to rnmpeie at the
Olympic Oamea of Mil,
The Amateur Athletic Union regrete
that It permitted Mr. Thorpe to com
pete In amateur contests during the
past eeveral yeara. and will do every
thing? In Ha power to secure tha re
turn of prtaee and the 1 eadluatment
of points won by him, and will Imme
diately eliminate il recorde from
the books.
OUVTAVUI T Kiunr.
President Amateur Athletic Union
and VI -e preel.t.mt of Amerloan
Olympic Committee.
JAMBS K. OleUVAef,
Chairman National Registration
Committee. Secretary Amateur Ath
letic Union and Secretary Ameri
can Olympic Committee
BARTOW B WIJKK8.
Chairman Ler'.alatlon Committee
A. A. U. and Vice-President Amu
lean Olympic Committee.
Dated New York City,
Jan. It, 1ll (Hlgnad)
w
onn reaches mt that tha Boxing
I'ommtstlnn, not having heard
from Attorney-Oeneral t'armody.
will postpon Its hearing of the Um
pire A. 0H acheduled for to-morrow,
over for a wk. At the culmination of
laat waek'e Inquiry, the Hosing Com
ni let' on requested the Htate'e attorney
te formulate a eerlea of iiueatlons that
could loyally he ueked the MoMal.on
boya pro mo tan Of Hi ICmpire ttlub, as
to then mauagemeni of the orowd want-
lug to aee the t'roea-III vers bout. Lei
ua bona thai the Attorns, -tseiieral will
speedily aee hla way clear ta assist tha
Hexing t'oiumlael n In Ita Investigation
of the Kmplr Club, fur a that be
gan with audi a noisy display of pyro-
leohnlca auouldn t be allots ad lo eimnaar
down Ui esha arltliout the parties eon-
temed and lh aportliig publlo recelv-
Ing ama eort of eattefaotaea.
BV -BBBBJg7 SBBBBBk esBaas M BgBgBgBBl gap gf raBBBBBKBBBaaM-grBTBBBeaBt W tsW MB aBBkB. fT aBBBBBl BBBBBBa I a
bOYJ MVS T 9E
CARCtVA. NfjVW-A.tjAyJ"
THORP SIGNS WITH
PlMTU FOR $7,000,
SAYS THIS STORY.
Jim Thorpe won't have to watt
long for a lob now that he's heeni
proven a profeeelonel, fey word tomee
to-day from rtttabury that the Plratee
have already elgned the remove tndlaa
to play Bret baaa. It ta boUooed that
the oeattaet was eigaed laat fall,
after whloh Thorp -vontlnned to take
part ta aanatonr ouataata. Beailalng
tho Bedeklns great drasrUg power,
the Vtratoa win pay Thorpe fT.OOO n
year, aoeerdlag to the reports. Tha
traeVerg olub only landed Tborpe
after spirited blading with other Mg
loag-ae teama. Washington eapaotelly
waa eery aaalena to oonral tho ladles.
E
.ocal Boxer Just Prepared
for Kilbane (jo in Final
Home Bout.
Whan local fight fans ace Johnny
Dundee, the levai lilllu east side buxr,
In acii. m again It may 1 tiiat ha' II hae
the tllte of faathayn eight ohamplon at
tarbed to his name, fur hla bout aainal
Special Delivery lllrsch of hicagn. at
tha Olympic A. 0, was his laat until
after Ids championship i cutest with
Johnny Kllbent at l.us Angeles on Api ll
15. Dundee ami his manager, afcJOtty
Montaith. plan It) laava fo.- tho oavt at
once no all their filendn war on hand
to see In "getaway" battle.
iflrsch aas easy fur the Italian lad
fiom atari to finish, the fifth round be
ing the only one that was in hla PJsVOr.
Ab Altai) la nuw manager of Ulrach
and he was in his corner aliomerlng him
llh words or advice, but thla didn't
ftaae Dundee, wbu kept after his orspu
nent all the way and at tunes scored so
often that the Windy City lad w.is
nearly all in trhag the bell oUtnged.
A. A. U. Might
In Some Famous
Evidence Used
BY BOZEMAN BULGER.
FOIt
A.
go
''It playing summer haNehall down
U, csueht Jim Thorpe, the Indian nthlete. red handed and with the
no. is, altlnitiitli not until the noted
athlete must return those prlr.es, medals and honor he won at the Olympic
Itainea to a fee kinaa and empernra. A merry time did many of our beat known
atnnteur put lu to-duy looking up their n nmaieur standing. Thorpe along
with his confession to the A. A I. Vhre.iteus to lift ths curtain on othor per
formers, who he sHi a are tn fie aams boat with lilnweir. Now the queetlon la
"what I an amateur?" Juet how niu h money It takes tn make a man a pro
fessional la not at hand, but you can go and bet your a x that the Rocky Mount
team on witeh Thnrpa played didn't com within striking distance of the limit
In fixing up Thorpe
Ae we understand It. amateura around
thee,- parts ore Htlowed gt.nd men! nnd
travelling expenses, a thlitg which .Tim
never got In the Kastem Month Carolina
league. "How you want you algs?" 1
all h ever got for breakfast, and those
Individual bowl", like canary bh-d bath
tubs. In whl -h they served the dinnera,
were never Intended to rob a man of
his amateur standing.
GOLIATH GETS DECISION BE
CAUSE DAVID WAS A "PRO."
Jim Thorp la a professional, but
he Is the only man ever aocused of It In
that league Arthur Devlin, the ex-Qlant.
aye ha had been sway from there for
two yeara before people ever regarded
him aa a professional and Frank Smith
saye the ps-pera sometimes call him an
amateur now.
Thla thine of dxyging up the dop on
a fallow nearly a year after the haa won
the prtaee eounda Mke a fallow running
tor oflloe. Incidentally It le understood
that the Amateur Athletic l'nlon lias
Just duty up the dope on David when he
uirw awai eiiia, ........o-t. laswsat
or wliatever It wte. and having found
j him to be a profaaalonal have decided
"an vsnimui o v.. ..........o
Thar have marked tnr the blue ribbon
record accredited to Wtlllain Tell, he
oauee It was discovered thet HIS and
hla eon lied been In the iippla peddling
buB)M-1 tw xwo yes is before tb shot
wu nrd.
in inspect .on at ths A. A. IV filet
shows an absolut blank wheiwuri
ahanld ha eegera vo the aaaaa ef
SOM OTHEK VveU-KAJOUAJ
"AMATeo" ivilt GtrT aiK
Thorpe' Confession
Department of the Inieilor,
United States Indian (service.
Carllale, Pa.. Jan. at. an
James hi. VuUlvan. New Vora. N. I.I
Deai Hlr When In Interview with Mr. Oanoy staling that I had played
baaaball on the Wlnetun-ttaleia team waa abown me I told Mr. Warner thnt
It waa not true, and In fact X did not play on that team tint au uiU'ih has
beeu eald In tha papers elnoe then that 1 went to tba aahovl authurltlea :h s
oiornlng and told them juel what there wae in the stories.
1 played baseball at Hooky Mount and at Fayette 111, N. In the tum
mer of 10 and 1V10 under my own nam, on the same teama I played with
ware eeveral college men frvui tbe North who were earning money by Uall
playlng during their vacations and who were regarded ee amateura at home.
1 did not play for the money there waa in it, because my property brings m
In enough money to live on, but because 1 liked tu play ball. 1 wae nut very
wise to the waya of the world and did not realize that this was wiong and
it would make me a professional In track eports. although I learned from
tbe other playars that It would be hotter for me not to let any on know thai
I was playing, and for that reaaon I never told any one at tbe school elbout
It until to-day.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1913-01-28/ed-1/?sp=11&q=THORPE+JAMES+Olympic+Thorpe+James</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Expressions of Sympathy for
Jim Thorpe, Carlisle Indian,
Heard on Every Side Today.
TROPHIES RETURNED
TO JIM SULLIVAN
Foreign Nations Expected to
Renew Complaints Against
American System.
May Join Pirates.
Jim' Thorpe, according to reports
from Pittsburgh today, irill play
first base for the Pirates this
season, baring signed a con
tract last fall. From Carlisle
it Is reported that Thorpe Is1
undecided as yet jnst what he
Trill do, now that be is declared
a professional athlete.
NEW YORK, Jan. 2S.-Nothlng but
expressions of sympathy were heard In
every quarter over the plight of "Jim"
Thorpe, the big Indian athlete who was
yesterday "condemned out of his own
mouth" of. the sin of professionalism
because he played baseball a true;
American sport with a now defunct
league and has thus been read out of
amateur athletics and all of the tro
phies that he won by his gallant work
in Sweden ordered returned to the
Olympic committee. But there was
much, bitter condemnation for the man
agement of the A. A. U. for the man
ner in which it has handledthe Thorpe
case as contrasted with hundreds of
cases of real professionalism right here
In the metropolitan district.
The committee right, it was conceded,
in repudiating 'Thorpe and In ordering
the return of all his prizes. But there
was an undercurrent of resentment
that the committee had not taken cog
nizance of the fact that the big Indian
had played professional baseball be
fore his Olympic entry was put
through. It was admitted that If the
A. A. O. had any real method of Inves
tigation, the farce which will certainly
be seized on by the nations on the other
oc seized on oy uie nations on me oinan
lde of the "pond" to renew their at-,
tacks upon American athletic methods
would have been prevented.
The present registration methods of
the A. A. U. are antiquated. There are
any number of professionals masque
rading as amateurs and it was pointed
out that Thorpe, who. played the game
for the love of it. had been disqualified
although he received very little money.
while Brlckley. the Harvard football
star: Flynn, or Tale, and a score of
others during the recent football season
earned more for one article from their
pens and in most instances they did
not actually write a sentence than
Thorpe did for a whole season of ball
playing "In the bushes." But they re
tain their amateur standing.
Recognition is Due.
There was a general feeling among
the real lovers of athletics today that
something should be done to give Jim
Thorpe the recognition that his mighty
deeds deserved despite the fact that all
of the records he established are now
automatically wiped out by the action
of the A. A. U. Thorpe's clean breast
of the matter, saving time and trouble,
was accepted as a real proof of sports
manship and although the tronhles of
V.I. iH fwiA nt
royalty will go to others, sporting ex
jjci ka uuautuivuoij t,ui.v.ut;u luvaj mat.
Thorpe would be more respected than
ever for not having tried "to lie out of
It," as other "amateurs" have done In
the past and have "gotten away with
IC because the A. A. V. committees
have not been too persistent In their
investigations.
The trophies won by Thorpe are al
ready en route to, Jim Sullivan's ofTIce
and will be immediately sent back to
Sweden to be given to the contestants
who finished second to the incomparable
Indian.
America Still Leads.
As a result of tlio disqualification of
Thorpe, the United States still remains)
in the lead in the readjusted program
of the results of the last Olympic games
but Sweden gets second place In the
list. Is the Decathlon Swedish athletes
finished second, third and fourth to the
American and the five points arc added
to their total, making them 32 and put-
tin r them ahead of Finland.
The total of the United States Is re
duced from S5 to 76 through the loss of
the Thorpe points. J J. Donahue, of
the United States, takes second instead
of third In the Penthlon first honors In
which now go to P. Ft. Ble. of Norway,
p. X- Lukeman of Canada moves up
from fourth to third. This gives Nor
way 7 points Instead of 4 and Canada
16 Instead of 15.
Here's Thorpe's Letter.
"Department of the Interior,
"United States Indian Service,
"Carlisle, Pa.. Jan. 16. 1911
'James E. Sullivan. New York, JC. Y.
"Dear Sir: When the interview with
JIr. Clancy, statin? that I had plajed
baseball on the. Winston-Salem team
was shown me. I told Mr. Warner that
It was not true, and, In fact, I did not
play on that team. Hut so much has
been said In the papers since then that
T went to the school authorities this
morning and told them just what there
was in the stories.
"I played baseball at Rocky Mount
and at payetteville, N. C, In the sum
mer of 1939 and 1910 under my own
name. On the same teams I "played
with were several college men from
the North who were earning money by
ball playing during their vacation and
who were regarded as amateurs at
home.
Money No Object.
"I did not play for the money there
was in it, because my property brings
me in enough money to live on, buf be
cause I Hked to play ball. I was not
very wlse-to the ways of the world, and
did not realize that this was wrong,
and it would make me a professional in
track sports, although I learned from
the other players that it would be 'better
for me not to let any one know that I
was playing, and for that reason I
never told any one at the school about
it until today.
"In the fall of 1S11 I applied for re-
T
REGISTRATION
IT'S NO
G AvR Clo-SiMG OUT ftLLTrfe I At TtfS SrKG TO "X I 7 jjjjgf 51 I
I CtfPY f U PLAY ovefc somp VF it's swiss OR. r !5R?"hot tdMalg" r U Ke 'susraJhe&s S SOR, &TF T
y ZliVL. ViHENSHEHres-mB.y pffplSf 'V id TTfe LABEL MEEhS IS NT THERE i Tb"Te SUTCtls
pp p
I Hr i i i i i .4,1
BRITISH ATHLETES
HP
E
Glad That Thorpe Made Frank
Confession and Pleased at
Return of Trophies Won.
LONDON. Jan. .-BrlUsh athletes
generally expressed approval of the ex-
pose qf Jim Thorpe, the Indian athlete,
as a professional, and also commended
th. Ampriun for hi. frank- ronr,!on
Because of Thorpe's Indorsement by
.-i;;l. im;i x-,i..." j
the American Olympian committee and
the Amateur Athletic Association,
Thorpe's status as an amateur was ac
cepted without question by the Interna
tional council," said Capt. W. S. Jones,
secretary of the British Olympian Com
mittee. "In view of his complete confession
of professionalism, I am certain that
th amateur authorities of hII countries
will heartily approve the verdict that
mi ",i i
Thorpe must relinquish his honors won
at Stockholm and restore his trophies."
Jockey Club Refuses
To Discuss Brown
The officials of the Jockey Club de
cline absolutely to discuss the attack
of H. D. "Curley"" Brown, promoter
of the race meets at the Laurel track,
until they have conferred with counsel.
August Belmont, chairman of the club.
may Issue a statement In a few days.
tnougn, tt is saiu, jiawara aurxe, -manager
of the Havre de Grace track, says
he is not in sympathy with Brown and
is well satisfied with conditions at his
track and with the supervision of the
Jockey Club.
"The Jockey Club has not refused to
sanction Laurel's dates for next fall."
said Assistant Secretary Daingerfield
yesterday. "Brown has been notified
that he has not obeyed certain rules
and that Laurel's fall meeting Is too
far away Just now to warrant any
action by the stewards. Brown agreed
In the first place to obey the rules."
Guard Completes Its
Basketball Schedule
Captain Edwards has completed the
last half of the schedule of the Dis
trict National Guard Basketball League
the original dates having included
games up to January 31, only. The re
mainder of the dates follow.
February 3. List vs K 2nd; February
5. E2d vs Klst; Februar 7. F2d vs
Elst; February 10. Klst vs Klst; Feb
ruary. 12. List vs F2d; February 14
.-J1 T-l I
.s. JfK.: p.7...' riS1 V?-,1'
TT C-V0i.-'k', 7,
ruary 21, Elst vs KW, February 21,
List vs km; j-eDruary 25. Klst vs
E2d; February 2S, Elst vs F2d.
March 3. List vs K2d; March 5. E 2d
vs Klst; March 7. F2d vs Elst; March
JO, pick teams of either league.
admission to this school and came back
to continue my studies ami take part
In the school sports, and, of course, I
wanted to get on the Olympic team and
take a trip to Stockholm I had Mr.
Warner send In my application for reg
istering In the A. A. U., after I hau
answered the questions and signed It,
and I received my card, allowing me
to compete in the winter meets and
other track sports.
Realizes Mistake.
"I never realized until now what a
big mistake I made by keeping tt a I
secret about my ball playing, and I am
sorry I did so. I hope it will be partly
excused by the fact that I was simply
an Indian schoolboy, and did not know
all about such things. In fact, I did
not know that 1 was doing wrong be
cause I was doing what I knew several
other college men had done, except that
they did not use their own names.
"I have always liked sport and only
played or ran races for the fun of the
thing and never to earn money. I have
received offers amounting to thousands
of dollars since my victories last sum
mer, but I have turned them all doun
because I did not care to make money
from my athletic skill.
"I am sorry. Mr. Sullivan, to have It
all spoiled In this way. and I hope the
Amateur Athletic Union and the people
will not be too hard in judging me.
"l'ours truly,
"JAMES THORPE."
i
the
Its Action
EASY MATTER TO HOLD A JOB.
A. A. U. FACES STORM OF PROTEST
METHODS, MEANS AND MEN
Thorpe's Case Arouses Indigna
tion Everywhere at Ways of
Whitewashing Athletes.
By LOUIS A. DOUGHER.
Tn ftiA train cf th rhflrir of nrn
0..,
An.rin
X ui,j
all-around champion, and acknowledged
greatest football player of the season
of 191Z. come rea-not complaints against l
blJU .C..w.0 U M.S. W. AAW.t,.1.4.
if things go along as they have gen
erally In the past, everything will sim
mer down and the Indian athlete will
be the only sufferer.
Thorpe's case is but one to encage the
amateur athletic world this season. He
admits he played bush league baseball,
and. on that account, he Is to be
blacklisted by the A. A. U. and to have
his records expunged from the record
books. His trophies, won at the-Swedlsh
Olympic games, will be handed over
to Swedish athletes who finished sec
ond to him, and the American commit
tee will apologize for entering a pro
fessional. The matter will then be set
tled. However, followers of athletics will
hardly be satisfied. There Is so much
two-faced action by A. A. U. officials
I every year that the murmuring Is rap
idly Increasing into a roar against their
methods.
According to rules now In vogue, a
college baseball player taking money
from a bush league club in the summer
Is considered a professional and barred
from appearing in sports under the
jurisdiction of the A. A. U. That Is the
rule which hits Jim Thorpe, the un
tutored Indian who knew so little of
chicanery that he used his own name
while college men on his team went
under pseudonyms.
What Amateurism Is.
Amateurism Is supposed to be sport
for sport's sake. An athlete Is supposed
to engage In It merely for the love of
It. accepting nothing for his efforts,
save the prizes offered to winners.
That's what it Is supposed to be but It
Isn't..
Let any man In Washington endeavor
to run an amateur meet in this city and
endeavor to obtain some of the crack
athletes from the New York clubs and
see what he is up against. No, they
don't -want appearance money, it is
called "expenses." That's why It some
times costs J10O to have a champion
travel from New York to Washington
or Boston, a six-hour ride at the most.
There are various emoluments con
nected with official A. A. U. positions, i
...W J,
They mount up in the course of a year,
?.nd tnat' wh- in ev?"' department of
ln organization o
fflclals may bo found
representing defunct organizations. It
exists right here In the South Atlantic
division of the A. A. U.
The Turn Of It.
The peculiar turn of the amateur
view may be shown by two Incidents
of late. A college baseball player
earns money In summer because of
h baseball ability.
They don't have
professional football teams, but New
York papers were willing, and did, to
Pay Charlie Brlckley and "Lefty"
Flynn fat sums for the use of their
names over football stories last fall.
Roger a Minstrel
Now we know what Roger Bresnahan is going to do with the money he
received from Mrs. Helene Hathaway Britton, owner of the Cardinals. He's
going into the minstrels. He's going to hold "Honey Boy" Evans to a prom
ise made j'ust the moment the "Rajah" was fired by his boss. Furthermore,
with his money in the show, Roger is going to act as interlocutor, a position
for which he is eminently fitted. Yep, Roger looks great in an open-face
shirt.
Georgie Evans, beloved of every baseball man in the land, asked his friend
Bresnahan to purchase part of the stock in the company, perhaps never
.thinking the Cardinal boss would ever accept the offer. But Roger is now
willing to take a chance with the easy money he got from the Cardinals, and
may close the, deal before the minstrel troupe hits the Capital February g
for a week at the Columbia Theater.
Washington times,
in Case of
Had Brlckley and Flynn not been ex
cellent football players they never
wbuld have received that money. They
earned it by their ability on the grid
iron. Percy Haughton. for five years pro
fessional head coach of the Harvard
football eleven, enters in the 'amateur
racquet championships, and no com
ment Is made upon his action. His
entry Is accepted and he plays, win
ning his match last Saturday in Bos
ton. If a man Is professionalized, in any
way, shape or manner how can he
engage in amateur sport? Yet Haugh
tdn is a professional at football and
an 'amateur at racquets. If being pro
fessionalized is taking money for ath
letic f knowledge or ability, why. isn't
Brickleya professional t Under'-tb!
very rule Jim Thorpe today stands as
a professional atnieie,
The time has come for a new deal
GUARDSMEN WILL
BACK MEMORIALS
Captain Edwards, of N. G. A. A., Declares A. A. U. Has No Right
to Interfere With Ten -Mile Run to Be Held
Here Feb ruary 8.
By KIRK C.
"At least a half dozen athletes from
the National Guard Athletic Association
will enter the ten-mile run to be held
by the Memorial Athletic Club Febru
ary 8, and this number may be swelled
to ten before the entries close."
Above are the words of Capt. C. Eu
gene Edwards, president of the Nation
al Guard A. A., and every member of
that organization is going to stick by
him in his effort to have athletics in
the District of Columbia run on an un
hampered bafcis.
"The Amateur Athletic Union has no
jurisdiction over tho proposed run of
the Memorial A. C: and so long as the
athletes are amateurs, they arc quali
fied to run under the Amateur Federa
tion of the District of Columbia, which
body Washington's athletes are trying
to adhere to," continued Captain Ed-1
wards.
Furthermore, Captain Edwards chal
lenges the chairman of the South At
lantic Association of the A. A. V. in his
authority to forbid those who wish to
enter the Memorial run. from ho doing.
Captain Edwards claims that the A.
A. U. officials in Washington, which in
clude the chairman of the registration
committee and the vice president, were
not elected by the Washington clubs,
but were chosen for those positions at
a meeting In Baltimore nt which no
athletic club of the District was renre-
I sented. He therefore argues that these
officials, neither or whom represents any
athletic organization, have no right to
a place on any rommlttce or In any
office of the Amateur Athletic Union.
"We want the followers of sporting
events In Washington to understand
that we have withdrawn from the A A.
V. We are not fighting that body; but
we have organized a District Amateur
Federation under which head we arc
prospering better than we ever did un
der the A. A. U.," were Captain Ed
Tuesday, januahy28, 1913
Jim Thorpe, Who Admits His Being a "Pro"
In the A. A. U. Everybody acknowl
edges without dispute the undoubted
ability offJIm Sullivan and laud him
for his years of effort. But It is about
time that the officials of the A. A. U.
were chosen for their ability, not for
their pull. Surround Sullivan by u
group of former athletes who know
something and have spine enough to
entorce their own rules, and tne A. A.
U. will cease to be the laughing stock
of the country. Indeed, Thorpe's case
comes close to making it the laughing
stock or the civilized world. There are
too many sea'-lawyers Identified with
the organization now. There are too
many methods In vogue undermining
the very object of the A. A. U.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032923/1913-01-29/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Thorpe+Olympic&st=text&r=-0.284,-0.078,1.568,1.568,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Thorpe Played Baseball
.For Money Three
Years Ago
NEW YORK, Jan. 27. James
Thorpe the Indian athlete and
Olympic champion admitted that the
charges of professionalism against
him were true in a letter sent to the
registration committee of the Ama
teur Athletic Union which met to
day to investigate the case. He ad
mitted he played baseball on a pro
fessional team three years ago.
The Olympic hero admitted nlay-
ing ball in North Carolina during
vacation not for money, but love of
the game. He didn't know it was
wrong as other college men played.
Thorpe's winning of the Panthalon
Decathlon events at Stockholm and
later his wonderful performances
which won the all-arund champion
ship stamped him as the most mar
velous athlete of modern times. He
will be obliged to return all trophies
won and the standing of the Olymp
ic games will be revised giving the
men first places who were second
to the Indian. The loss of points
won by Thorpe still leaves a wide
margin for the United States at the
Olympic games.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1913-01-31/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Thorpe+Jim&st=text&r=0.19,-0.054,1.289,1.31,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>UIM" THORPE
THORPE AFTER
ALLNIGHT 1
Indian Turns Down Terms of
Five Other Clubs to Be
come a Giant.
James Thorpe. Ihe greatest living
athlete, recentl) declared a processional.
bus sUned a contract to play e th the
N'ew York Hlants for the season isf
191. Whether he becomes a pitcher or
a first baseman makes little difference
lo Manager Mi lira w,
"A -wonderful athlete like Thorpe,"
says the tllant leader, "ought to have In
him the makings of a great ball player.
H has the muscle and the brain, and
It Is up to me to locate the spot where
be will be of most value to tile earn."
llislruw personally conducted the
negotiations for the Indian athlete
without the aid of a scout. He spent
the whole night In conference with
Thorpe and those on whom the Indian
dapnndg for advice. It was nearly day
light before tiie affair was setllud and
HcQraw got to bed.
Tiie tip got out before official news
of the dial reached the New York
headquarters. Secretary Foster re
ceive I a telegram from Thorpe at I
o'clock this gftsmOOfl to the effect thst
lie had signed the contract and (be
papers would be forwarded Imme
diately. M'GRAW BEAT ALL THE SCOUTS
TO INDIAN.
Just what salary Thorpe la to receive
lias not and h I not bi announced. It
known, though, that the narurea are
Pi ex.-eea of 11,, VO Frank lliin' roft, busi
ness manager of the fUnntlMlggl Hods,
who w oil to Carlisle lo sign tha Indian,
wired August Herrmann this momlng
that ha hail failed In Ida queai tint ha
had offered Il,.'si0, Put that the Ulanta
hud outbid him. Bancroft also wired
that rtve a. 'outs were at Carlisle all day
vesteiilay making bids for Thorpe's
services.
When Thorpe announced a few days
SgO thai lie would now have to turn to
baseball foT a living be Intimated thill
he wou-ld like to play In Nuw York.
M.iiraw was lick in be.' at the time, Put
b.. was tfiophono.l the t.p and gut out
ot bad to he on the lob.
Thorp will lepoit to Ihe Hlants on
I'.-ii. Itj and win go to Harltn with in
i ci ults. If be should develop Into a
big league pit, her New York will have
the only fullshlooded Indian hattery that
as, all has svsr knotm Ohbjf Meyers
ha always had a deep .'Iking for Thoroe,
and will do everytb.ng in his power to
Utah him a glWCIgg If Thorpe should
show ro marks of a pitcher -a bl
IcagUtr -M 'iiA trill try him al first
a-' He wili also be given a cnance
n the outfield.
In signing Thorpe, M.Hraw deiisies
teat I n- gmOUnl of money was no con
ttdsmtlon, Kg matter hoar much lu
lilaiils sild, Thorpe, lis ii draw ing -ard.
nill more than reimburse Lheiii,
It is unl kely that Thoipv will gat o
regular lob the llrsl season, but he aU
he kept oil the In nch to alisorb g, i,.
pra I knowlsdg of the game. If he
hould dOVSlop Into a Mrst year wonder
John Mctlraw wIM Pu tliu proudeat
manggsr iti basei.aii.
Jim Thorpe Is only twenty-four years
old and Is lust in bis prime aa un ath
iit Ht is the leal s as for a bail
play.-r and h.s gnotflSdga of athletl
i i general will be of i value to
him In getting In shape After seeing
tllm pig! f""i ill no one cotil.i question
til 1 no.</text>
      </result>
      <result>	
  <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1913-02-01/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Thorpe+James+Olympic+Thorp+THORPE</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text>THORPE AGREES TO
TERMS OFFERED BY
M'GRAW FOR GIANTS
Indian Athlete, Star of Olympic Games, Declared
Professional by A. A. U., After Returning Tro?
phies Won, Adopts Baseball as Profession.
Mans League Teams Bid For His Services.
New York. January JI. James Thorpe, the greatest living athlete
recently declared a professional, has signed a contract to play with the
New York iiants for the season of l j 13 Whether he become* pitcher
or a first baseman makes little difference to Manager Met 1 raw.
"A wonderful athlete like Thorpe." says the (iiant leader, "ought
to ha\e in him the makings of a great ball player. He has the muscle
and the brain, and it is up to me to locate the s|x>t where he will be of
most value to the team."
McOaw jHTsonalh conducted the negotiation for the Indian athlete
without the aid of a Mill. He spent the whole night in conference with
Thorjx; and those on whom the Indian depends for advice. It was
nearlv daylight before the affair was settled and Met ir.tw got to bed.
The tip got out before official news of the deal reached the New
York headquarters. Secretary l-oster received a telegram from Thorpe
this afternoon to the effect that he had signed the contract and the
pafters would be forwarded immediately.
Salary Not Known.
Just what salary Thorpe is to rec eive has not .tnd will not be an?
nounced. It is known, though, that the figures are in excels of $4,500.
Krank Bancroft, business manager of the Cincinnati Reds who went
to Carlisle to sign the Indian, wired August Hermann to-day that he
had failed in bisquest; that he had offered ?4,500, but that the Ciants
had outbid him. Bancroft also wired that five scouts were at Carlisle
all day vesterdav making bids tor Thori>e*s scr\ii<-.
When Thorpe announced a f?w ?lay
ago that he would now have to tun
to baseball for a living he intimutce
that be would like to play in N we York
Metlraw warf ?ick m bed at the tin,,
but he was telephoned the tip and gol
out of bed to be on tho job.
Thorpe will report to the tliants ir
February 1?, anil will go to Marlin with
the ret ruits. If he should develop mrc
a big l.-ague pitcher. New York will
have the only full-blooded Indian
battery that baseball has ever known
hlef Meyer* baa always had g d. j
liking for Thorpe, and will do ?verjr
thmg in his power to make him a sue
cess. If Thoipe should show no mark?
of a pitcher, u big leaguer hfoflrOO
will try him at first base. Mo will also
be given a chance in the outfield In
signing Thorpe Mi lira* declares that
the amount of money was no considera?
tion. No matt'-r how much the .re?
paid. Thorpe, as a drawing card. Orill
more than reimburse them
Ma> Flay on Heneh.
It is unlikely that Thorpe will get a
regular job tho first s? ason but he will
be kept on the bench to absorb the gen?
eral knowledge of the game If bo
should develop info a fl*~t '.'ear wopder
.lohn McOraw will bo the proudest
manager in baseball. e
Thorpe, it was announced by I'resi
dent Han Johnson, of the American
League, is not a free agen'. Thorpe
Is under contract with the Kayttovillo
N. I' club, and it will be 00000001
to negotiate for his release through
the owner of that club. President
Johnson received this information in a
telegram from Secretary Karrcll, of
the National Association. In 1910
Thorpe signed a contract with the
Rocky Mount. N. C.. club, el tlji
a month Later, he was transferred
Kayetteville. j,i.d reserved by that
club.
Jim Thorpe is only twenty-four years
old. and is just in his prime as an
athlete tie is the ideal size for a
bail player. and bis knowledge
of ethtetice in general will be of im?
mense value lo tutu iii getting in shape
After seeing him play football, no one
could question his gamcn. s
Oolng to New Vork.
"Thorpe will tie here to-moin.w at
2 o'clock, wh' n at the cttth't OfSoea
he will sign a contract to play with
the Oiants said Manager M< draw
to-night. He adde-d that he first
thought, ejf engaging Thorpe reotordmx.
when the publicity given the Indian's
disbarment from the Amateur Ath?
letic L'nion. ana the statement that
several Western managers were trying
to sign him. put the idea into the
manager's head.
"I got Thorpe on the ong distance
telephone in Carlisle. Pa said Mc?
Oraw. "and he accepted my offer
Later I got a telegram fron, him OOO)
firming his verbal eeeepCOgftOg He
preferred to come ro New York, and
I offered him more money than the
others, too.''
McCiraw said the salary was a pn?
transaction, and would not dis?
cuss it.
Thorpe ought to make a good all
around man. M'Oraw added f
expect he will accompany the team
South when the spring training season
opens, and then we II try him out and
sec whete he can do his best work.''
.lames K. Sullivan, secretary of the
Amateur Athletic l'nion. announced
to-ntght- that he had received the chal?
lenge trophios won by Thorpe in the
Olympic games last night and would
send them to Kris'ian Hellstrom sec?
retary of the Swedish Olympic Com?
mittee Mr Sullivan said also that
the all-round trophy won by Thorpe
at Celtic Park la.-f September had
been sent from Carlisle- with the Olym?
pic trophies and now was in the pos?
session of the Amateur Athlet]?- l'nion
It will go to Bredemus. formerly of
Princeton t'niversity. who was seconej
to Thorpe in the Celtic Park games.
THORPE MAKES ANNOUNCE.
MENT
Carlisle. Pa January II --lames
Thorpe the greatest athlete in the
worid. haa hern actually deluged get
only with major league baseball offers
but has been Mrtf saamped by cirrus,
vaudeville, n instre l prize fighters and
klnelred enterprise promoters since he
announced that he would be compelled
lo become a pr--fe?si?authorized the statement that he has
dei led to play professional baseball
and does not are to appear before the
put-Ii- in any other manner, except tee
fore starting in his baseball Work he
may give O few athletic exhibitions a*
indoor athlete meets The town of
1 arlisle has been a mc-ra for represent
stives of both major and minor league
baseball teams, and the local telegraph
wires have been burdened for the las*
ight hours with appeals to Thorpe
to bold hie dectelon as to bis future
un'i. managers and pr, ,n>.
'alk to him. This evening, beiweeer.
Thorpe pu? an end to the competition
for htm by announcing the* althoug*?
he had not signed a contract. he he?'
I't-.r his aeeurance to Manager John
I Mrfirte, of New York City, thet be
would ploy with the New York Olente.
ESTABLISH THORPE TROPHY
csrltele. Pa. Jonuery XI--A move?
ment hy which America ?o give
re ?ni? ten to Jim Thorpe who beete i
hOtrptone In the Olympic
games In ftwoedsn end who through
technicality hag *???n etrloped of hie
h. nor. and prizes giv en by th? f
o f Russia and tho King of Swede n. tree I
I -?..???d here to-day by citizens and
I n< v. IDKPM A POtllloa will be sent
H the American Athletic nion asking
that Thorpe's amateur statu? during
th.- Olympic Kann? lev affirmed be
OMNI <>f !he ri mote association of his
professional baseball experience with
i tra' k and field sports A popular
i penny fund for t he establishment of an
Amern an Thorpe trophy as an all
i around athletic trophy, irrespective
i of ra< cia-s ipiali Beat ions against
?he world, has also beer: started,
i This niovemen* was suggested by the
action of the Mayor and sou ettauane
of Vonkers. N' v.. In petitioning tb*
American Athletic Uaioa la reinstat?
Thorpe. </text>
      </result>
      <result>	
  <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045396/1913-02-02/ed-1/?sp=31&q=Thorpe+James+Olympic+Thorpes</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Jim Thorpes Prizes on Way Back
Athlete Blossoms Out as lnill
fleclged Professional
Ball Player.
By International Newe Serv-ic.
NTTW YORK. .Feb. 1. Jhn Thorpe,
tho wonderful Sac and Fox Indian
athlete, acclaimed by all the world as
tho greatest all-around athloto of
modern times, who. hue been sum
marily expelled from the Amateur
Athletic union and whose romaxkablo
Tocordn will bo stricken from all
athletic histories, all because ho
played baseball for money, h now a
full-fledged professional.
Thorpe has confessed to being j
guilty of professionalism. He- has
admitted that he played ball two
seasons with the Hooky fountain
team of the Northwestern Carolina
league. Ho defends himself by plead
ins ho waa only an Indian boy, half
educated, to tho .ways of whlto
folks.
This unexpected blotch on Thorpa's
career will necessitate tho forward
ing to tho nations of the world an
expression of humble apology on tho
part of Amorica for entering Thorpe
In tho Olympic gamea last 3uramer at
Stockholm.
Abovo are. shown the two prlaea
awarded to Thorpe for his victories in
the pantlielon and docathlon all
around athlotlo competitions. The
bust was tho prizo donated by tho
king of Sweden and tho Viking ship
waa presented by the cxar of Kussla.
Theso coveted trophies havo beon
aunendored by Thorpo to Socretary
Sullivan of the A. A. TJ., who has
ohipped them back to th royal
donors.
Tho bottom photograph is ono of
Thorpe's latest
James R Sullivan, secretary of the
Amateur Athletlo union, yesterday re
ceived from the Carlisle Indian scnool
the two handsome challengo trophies
won by James Thorpo at tho 3D12
Olympic games in Stoclcholm.
Thorpe also returned to tho A. A.
TJ. tho emblem of hte all-around
championship won at Celtic nark hint
September. The trophy and cham
pionship now reverts to John Brodo
mua of Princeton.
Tho Olympic trophies aro being re
turned to the Swedish Olympic au
thorities. Through Davis. Turner
Co. they wcro shipped on the steam
ship New York of tho American line.
They aro consigned to Christian
Hellstrom. secretary of tho Swedish.
Olympic committee.
Dispatches from Carlisle atato that
tho newspapers and eltizona of Ponn
nylyanla havo started a penny fund In
thft Intorrat of the profOKsIonallred
Thorpe. It In proposed to rulso suf
ficient capital at a penny a hcud to
purchaeo an American trophy for-tho
Indian to ruplaco tho gifts of tho
Eirropcan noverelgns.
."When he signed a, contract with th
Giants late this (Saturday) afternoon,
Jim Thorpo said he wanted to pitch,
but .McGraw expects to use him in
the outfield. ISven if Thorpe merely
nils on the benoh It is estimated his
presenco will attract more than
enough patronage to pay his nalary.
Thorpe this afternoon reconsidered
his promise to toll Secretary JameR
Sullivan of the A. A. IJ. th names
of other amateur athletes who played
basoball for money. Thorpo said that
as he was now a full-fledged profes
sional ho did not care to mix up In
amateur matters any moro. Scores of
amateur athletes will breatho easier
when they learn Thorpe's determina
tion not to turn Informor.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045487/1914-02-23/ed-1/?sp=28&q=THORPE+Thorpe+JIM+Jim&st=text&r=-0.303,-0.08,1.607,1.607,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>FULLERTON PICKS JIM THORPE TO BE THE BIG
BASEBALL SENSATION OF 1914
BY HUGH S. FULLERTON.
Jim Thorpe, Indian athlete, prom
ises to be-the most sensational base
ball player of i914-.
The astounding advances made by
this famous athlete in baseball have
furnished managers, owners, players
James Thorpe.
and experts with an object lesson that
threatens to overturn a lot of the tra
ditions of the national game, and
compel a radical change in existing
and accepted methods.
If Thorpe keeps the promise he has
given during the fall and winter, it
will be a triumph for JoTin McGraw
far greater than the winning of a
world's championship could be, and
it will make him the greatest man of
baseball. It will be a triumph for Mc
Graw's method of developing base
ball players.
Thorpe is the greatest athlete in
the world. He has proved it at almost
every style and kind of going. He won
the all-round championship during
the Olympic games. He had played
some baseball, but was only a medi
ocre player, and a wretched hitter
in school and on the little team with
which he played and professionalized
himself.
When the New York team signed
Thorpe to play baseball it looked as
if New York was merely putting over
a press agent scheme. Thorpe earned
his salary last season in advertising
he gave the team. But McGraw evi
dently had other ideas. There is one
thing about McGraw. If he has faith
in a -player he will stick to him longer
than any other manager would. He
calculated that Thorpe could run
faster, throw harder, jump further
and higher, and Was stronger than
any athlete in the world. With that
material he set out to make a real
baseball player.
Thorpe was an awkward fielder, er
ratic, a lunging, hard-swinging, un
certain batter, and he had most of the
faults that would be considered fatal
in young players. McGraw kept him
while almost any other manager
-vVauld have fired him as a hopeless
prospect before the training trip was
ended. All last summer McGraw
worked patiently with the Indian and
watched him. He was satisfied.
Thorpe, he discovered, also had
brains, and the Indian was studying,
watching the actions, of others and
adapting himself to certain methods
of others.
Then the round-the-world trip
started. Thorpe had the opportunity
of watching different kinds of ball
players, and he suddenly cut loose</text>
      </result>
      <result>
